<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certaine miscellany vvorks of the Right Honourable Francis Lo. Verulam, Viscount S. Alban. Published by William Rawley ...</title>
            <author>Bacon, Francis, 1561-1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1629</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 177 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01128</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1124</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100333</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836177</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836177</idno>
            <idno type="VID">433</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01128)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 433)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 691:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certaine miscellany vvorks of the Right Honourable Francis Lo. Verulam, Viscount S. Alban. Published by William Rawley ...</title>
                  <author>Bacon, Francis, 1561-1626.</author>
                  <author>Rawley, William, 1588?-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 166 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. Hauiland for Humphrey Robinson, dwelling at the signe of the three Pigeons in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1629.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>"Considerations touching a vvarre with Spaine", "An advertisement touching an holy vvarre", "An offer to our late soveraigne King Iames, of a digest to be made of the lawes of England", and "The history of the reigne of King Henry the Eighth" each has separate dated title page; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:433:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:433:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CERTAINE Miſcellany Works OF THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, FRANCIS Lo. Verulam, <hi>Viſcount</hi> S. ALBAN.</p>
            <p>PVBLISHED By <hi>WILLIAM RAWLEY,</hi> Doctor of Diuinity, one of his Maieſties Chaplaines.</p>
            <p>LONDON, ¶ Printed by <hi>I. Hauiland</hi> for <hi>Humphrey Robinſon,</hi> dwelling at the ſigne of the three Pigeons in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1629.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:433:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:433:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue thought good, as a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, to the Labours, and Memory, of that Noble Lord, the Lo. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſcount S. Alban,</hi> to collect into one, theſe few, rather Parcells, than luſt Works, of his excellent Pen. Which I haue done for theſe Cauſes. Firſt, to vindicate the Wrong, his Lordſhip ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb facs="tcp:433:3"/> by a corrupt, and ſurreptiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Edition, of that <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> of his, <hi>Touching a Warre with Spaine,</hi> lately ſet forth. Secondly, by way of Preuention, to exempt, from the like Iniury, &amp; Defacements, thoſe other <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> of his, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained. Laſtly, to ſatisfie the Deſires of ſome, who hold it vnreaſonable, that any the Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neations of that Pen, though in neuer ſo ſmall a Modell, ſhould not be ſhewen to the World. I know, it carries the Excuſe with it, after the <hi>Authors</hi> Death, to publiſh <hi>Fragments.</hi> Therefore I will make none. Theſe <hi>Works,</hi> being all, for the Argument, <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill,</hi> I cannot repreſent better, than in Reſemblance of <hi>Ariſtotles
<pb facs="tcp:433:3"/> Parua Naturalia,</hi> to account them as his Lordſhips <hi>Parua Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litica.</hi> Howſoeuer, I doubt not, but euery Iudicious <hi>Reader,</hi> fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of his Lordſhips Spirit in them, will know them to be his; And will afford them, a Place of Reputation, amongſt his Greater <hi>Works.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. RAWLEY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:433:4"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:433:4"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CONSIDERATIONS</hi> Touching a WARRE With SPAINE.</p>
                  <p>VVritten about fiue yeeres ſince, and inſcribed to his MAIESTIE, At that time PRINCE OF <hi>WALES.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device of John Haviland</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>LONDON, ¶ Printed by IOHN HAVILAND for <hi>Humphrey Robinſon.</hi> 1629.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:433:5"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:433:5"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CONSIDERATIONS</hi> Touching a WARRE With SPAINE.</head>
                  <head type="sub">To the Prince.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Highneſſe hath an <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Name.</hi> It was a CHARLES that brought the Empire firſt into <hi>France;</hi> A CHARLES that brought it firſt into <hi>Spaine:</hi> Why
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:433:6"/> ſhould not <hi>Great Britaine</hi> haue his turne? But to lay aſide all that may ſeeme to haue a ſhew of Fumes and Fancies, and to ſpeake Solids: A <hi>Warre</hi> with <hi>Spaine,</hi> (if the King ſhall enter into it,) is a mighty Worke; It requireth ſtrong Materialls, and Actiue Motions. He that ſaith not ſo, is zealous, but not according to knowledge. But ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe, <hi>Spaine</hi> is no ſuch Giant: And he that thinketh <hi>Spaine,</hi> to be ſome great Ouermatch for this Eſtate, aſſiſted as it is, and may be, is no good Mint-man; But takes greatneſſe of Kingdomes according to their Bulke and Currency, and not after their intrinſique Value. Although there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I had wholly ſequeſtred my thoughts from Ciuill Affaires, yet becauſe it is a new Caſe, and concerneth my Country infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely, I obtained of my ſelfe, to ſet downe, out of long continued experience in Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Eſtate, and much Conuerſation in Bookes of <hi>Policie</hi> and <hi>Hiſtorie,</hi> what I thought pertinent to this Buſineſſe; And in all humbleneſſe preſent it to your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; Hoping, that, at leaſt, you will
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:433:6"/> diſcerne the ſtrength of my Affection, through the weakneſſe of my Abilities: For the Spaniard hath a good Prouerbe; <hi>Deſuarió ſiempre con la Calentura; There is no Heat of Affection, but is ioyned with ſome Idleneſſe of Braine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To a Warre are required; <hi>A Iuſt Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell; Sufficient Forces and Prouiſions;</hi> And <hi>a prudent Choyce of the Deſignes.</hi> So then, I will firſt <hi>iuſtifie</hi> the <hi>Quarrell,</hi> Secondly, <hi>ballance</hi> the <hi>Forces;</hi> and laſtly, propound variety of <hi>Deſignes</hi> for Choice, but not <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe</hi> the Choice; For that were not fit for a Writing of this Nature; Neither is it a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect within the leuell of my Iudgement; I being, in effect, a Stranger to the preſent Occurrences.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Warres</hi> (I ſpeake not of ambitious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datory <hi>Warres,</hi>) are <hi>Suits</hi> of <hi>Appeale</hi> to the <hi>Tribunall</hi> of <hi>Gods Iuſtice,</hi> where there are no <hi>Superiours</hi> on earth to determine the Cauſe. And they are (as ciuill pleas are,) <hi>Plaints,</hi> or <hi>Defences.</hi> There are therefore three iuſt Grounds of <hi>Warre</hi> with <hi>Spaine:</hi> One <hi>Plaint,</hi> Two vpon <hi>Defence.</hi> SALOMON
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:433:7"/> ſaith, <hi>A Cord of three is not eaſily broken:</hi> But eſpecially when euery of the lines will hold ſingle by it ſelfe. They are theſe. <hi>The Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of the Palatinate; A iuſt Feare of the Subuerſion of our Ciuill Eſtate: A iuſt Feare of the Subuerſion of our Church and Religion.</hi> For in the handling of the two laſt Grounds of <hi>Warre,</hi> I ſhall make it plaine; That <hi>Warres</hi> Preuentiue vpon <hi>Iuſt Feares,</hi> are true <hi>Defenſiues,</hi> as well as vpon Actuall <hi>Inuaſions:</hi> And againe, that <hi>Warres De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue</hi> for <hi>Religion,</hi> (I ſpeake not of <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion,</hi>) are moſt iuſt; Though <hi>Offenſiue Warres,</hi> for <hi>Religion,</hi> are ſeldome to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, or neuer, vnleſſe they haue ſome Mixture of <hi>Ciuill Titles.</hi> But all that I ſhall ſay in this whole Argument, will be but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ike Bottomes of Thred, cloſe wound vp, which with a good Needle (perhaps) may be flouriſhed into large Workes.</p>
                  <p>For the Aſſerting of the <hi>Iuſtice of the Quarrell,</hi> for the <hi>Recouery of the Palatinate,</hi> I ſhall not goe ſo high, as to diſcuſſe the Right of the <hi>Warre</hi> of <hi>Bohemia;</hi> Which if it
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:433:7"/> be freed from doubt on our part, then there is no Colour nor Shadow, why the <hi>Palatinate</hi> ſhould be retained; The Raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing whereof was a meere Excurſion of the firſt Wrong, and a Super-Iniuſtice. But I doe not not take my ſelfe to be ſo perfect in the Cuſtomes, Tranſactions, and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges of that Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> as to be fit to handle that part. And I will not offer at that I cannot maſter. Yet this I will ſay (in paſſage) poſitiuely, and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely: That it is impoſſible, an <hi>Electiue Monarchy,</hi> ſhould be ſo free and abſolute, as an <hi>Hereditary:</hi> No more than it is poſſible, for a Father, to haue ſo full Power and Intereſt, in an Adoptiue Sonne, as in a Naturall; <hi>Quia naturalis Obligatio fortior Ciuili.</hi> And againe, that Receiued <hi>Maxime</hi> is almoſt Vnſhaken, and Infallible; <hi>Nil magis Naturae conſentaneum eſt, quàm vt iiſdem modis Res diſſoluantur, quibus conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuuntur.</hi> So that, if the part of the <hi>People</hi> or <hi>Eſtate</hi> be ſomewhat in the Election, you cannot make them Nulls or Cyphers in the Priuation or Tranſlation. And if it bee
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:433:8"/> ſaid, that this is a dangerous Opinion, for the <hi>Pope, Emperour,</hi> and <hi>Electiue Kings;</hi> It is true, it is a dangerous Opinion, and ought to be a dangerous Opinion, to ſuch perſonall <hi>Popes, Emperours,</hi> or <hi>Electiue Kings,</hi> as ſhall tranſcend their limits, and become Tyrannicall. But it is a ſafe and ſound Opinion for their Sees, Empires, and Kingdomes; And for themſelues alſo, if they be wiſe; <hi>Plenitudo Poteſtatis, eſt pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo Tempeſtatis.</hi> But the chiefe Cauſe, why I doe not ſearch into this point, is, becauſe I need it nor. And in handling the Right of a <hi>Warre,</hi> I am not willing to intermix matter doubtfull, with that which is out of doubt. For as in Capitall Cauſes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in but one Mans life is in queſtion, <hi>in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorem vitae,</hi> the Euidence ought to bee cleare; So much more, in a Iudgement vpon a <hi>Warre,</hi> which is Capitall to Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands. I ſuppoſe therefore the worſt; That the <hi>Offenſiue Warre</hi> vpon <hi>Bohemia</hi> had beene vniuſt; And then make the Caſe; Which is no ſooner made, than reſolued; If it be made, not enwrapped, but plainly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:433:8"/> and perſpicuouſly. It is this in <hi>Theſi.</hi> An <hi>Offenſiue Warre</hi> is made, which is vniuſt in the Aggreſſour; The Proſecution and Race of the <hi>Warre,</hi> carrieth the <hi>Defendant,</hi> to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile and inuade, the Ancient and Indubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Patrimony of the firſt <hi>Aggreſſour,</hi> who is now turned <hi>Defendant;</hi> Shall he ſit downe, and not put himſelfe in <hi>Defence;</hi> Or if he be diſpoſſeſſed, ſhall he not make a <hi>Warre</hi> for the Recouery? No Man is ſo poore of Iudgement, as will affirme it. The Caſtle of <hi>Cadmus</hi> was taken, and the City of <hi>Thebes</hi> it ſelfe inueſted, by <hi>Phaebidas</hi> the <hi>Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> inſidiouſly, &amp; in violation of League: The Proceſſe of this Action drew on a Reſurpriſe of the Caſtell by the <hi>Thebans,</hi> a Recouery of the <hi>Towne,</hi> and a Current of the <hi>Warre</hi> euen vnto the walls of <hi>Sparta.</hi> I demand, was the Defence of the City of <hi>Sparta,</hi> and the Expulſion of the <hi>Thebans,</hi> out of the ancient <hi>Laconian Territories,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt? The ſharing of that part of the <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie</hi> of <hi>Millaine,</hi> which lieth vpon the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of <hi>Adda,</hi> by the <hi>Venetians,</hi> vpon Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract with the <hi>French,</hi> was an Ambitious
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:433:9"/> and vniuſt Purchaſe. This wheele ſet on going, did powre a <hi>Warre</hi> vpon the <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> with ſuch a tempeſt, as <hi>Padoua</hi> and <hi>Treuigi</hi> were taken from them, and all their <hi>Dominions</hi> vpon the <hi>Continent</hi> of <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> abandoned, and they confined within the Salt Waters. Will any man ſay, that the memorable Recouery and Defence of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doua,</hi> (when the Gentlemen of <hi>Venice,</hi> vnu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the <hi>Warres,</hi> out of the loue of their Country, became Braue and Martiall the firſt day;) And ſo likewiſe the <hi>Readeption</hi> of <hi>Treuigi,</hi> and the reſt of their Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, was matter of Scruple, whether iuſt or no, becauſe it had ſource from a Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell ill begunne? The <hi>Warre</hi> of the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Vrbin,</hi> Nephew to <hi>Pope Iulius</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, when he made himſelfe Head of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Mutiniers, was as vniuſt, as vniuſt mought be; A ſupport of deſperate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels; An Inuaſion of <hi>Saint Peters</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony; And what you will. The Race of this <hi>Warre</hi> fell vpon the loſſe of <hi>Vrbin</hi> it ſelfe, which was the <hi>Dukes</hi> vndoubted Right; Yet in this caſe, no Penitentiary,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:433:9"/> (though hee had enioyned him neuer ſo ſtrait Penance to expiate his firſt Offence,) would haue counſelled him to haue giuen ouer the purſuit of his Right for <hi>Vrbin;</hi> Which after he proſperouſly re-obtained, and hath tranſmitted to his family yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till this day. Nothing more vniuſt, than the Inuaſion of the <hi>Spaniſh Armada,</hi> in 88. vpon our Seas; For our Land was holy land to them, they mought not touch it; Shall I ſay therefore, that the Defence of <hi>Lisbon,</hi> or <hi>Cales,</hi> afterward, was vniuſt? There be thouſands of Examples; <hi>Vtor in Re non dubia Exemplis non neceſſarijs:</hi> The Reaſon is plaine; <hi>Warres</hi> are <hi>Vindictae;</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenges, Reparations. But Reuenges are not infinite, but according to the meaſure of the firſt Wrong, or Damage. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when a voluntary <hi>Offenſiue Warre,</hi> by the Deſigne or Fortune of the <hi>Warre,</hi> is turned to a neceſſary <hi>Defenſiue Warre,</hi> the Scene of the Tragedy is changed, and it is a new Act to beginne. For though they the particular actions of <hi>Warre,</hi> are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate in Fact, yet they are ſeparate and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:433:10"/> in Right; Like to croſſe Suits in <hi>Ciuill Pleas,</hi> which are ſometimes both iuſt. But this is ſo cleare, as needeth no further to be inſiſted vpon. And yet, if in things ſo cleare, it were fit to ſpeake of more or leſſe cleare, in our preſent Cauſe, it is the more cleare on our part, becauſe the Poſſeſſion of <hi>Bohemia</hi> is ſetled with the <hi>Emperor.</hi> For though it be true, that, <hi>Non datur Compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatio Iniuriarum;</hi> yet were there ſomewhat more Colour to detaine the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> as in the nature of a Recouery, in Value or Compenſation, if <hi>Bohemia</hi> had beene loſt, or were ſtill the Stage of the <hi>Warre.</hi> Of this therefore I ſpeake no more<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As for the Title of <hi>Proſcription</hi> or <hi>Forfeiture,</hi> wherein the <hi>Emperour</hi> (vpon the matter) hath beene Iudge and Party, and hath iuſticed himſelfe, <hi>God</hi> forbid but that it ſhould well endure an Appeale to a <hi>Warre.</hi> For certainly the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Heauen,</hi> is as well a <hi>Chancery,</hi> to ſaue and debarre Forfeitures, as a <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Common Law</hi> to decide Rights; And there would bee worke enough, in <hi>Germany, Italy,</hi> and other Parts, if Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:433:10"/> Forfeitures ſhould goe for good Titles.</p>
                  <p>Thus much for the firſt Ground of <hi>Warre</hi> with <hi>Spaine,</hi> being in the Nature of a <hi>Plaint,</hi> for the <hi>Recouery of the Palatinate;</hi> Omitting here that which mought be the Seed of a larger Diſcourſe, and is verified by a number of Examples; That whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is gained by an Abuſiue Treaty, ought to bee reſtored <hi>in Integrum.</hi> As wee ſee the daily Experience of this in <hi>Ciuill Pleas;</hi> For the Images of great things are beſt ſeene contracted into ſmall Glaſſes; Wee ſee (I ſay) that all <hi>Pretorian Courts,</hi> if any of the <hi>Parties</hi> be entertained or laid aſleepe, vnder pretence of Arbiterment or Accord, &amp; that the other <hi>Party,</hi> during that time, doth cautelouſly get the ſtart and aduantage at <hi>Common Law,</hi> though it bee to Iudgement and Execution; Yet the <hi>Pretorian Court</hi> will ſet backe all things <hi>in ſtatu quo priùs,</hi> no reſpect had to ſuch Euiction or Diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion. Laſtly, let there be no miſtaking; As if when I ſpeake of a <hi>Warre</hi> for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> I meant, that it
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:433:11"/> muſt be <hi>in lineâ rectâ,</hi> vpon that Place: For looke into <hi>ius faeciale,</hi> and all Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and it will be found to be without ſcruple; That after a Legation <hi>ad Res repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendas,</hi> and a Refuſall, and a Denuntiation or Indiction of a <hi>Warre,</hi> the <hi>Warre</hi> is no more confined to the Place of the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, but is left at large, and to choice, (as to the particular conducing De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes,) as Opportunities and Aduantages ſhall inuite.</p>
                  <p>To proceed therefore to the ſecond Ground of a <hi>Warre</hi> with <hi>Spaine;</hi> We haue ſet it downe to be, <hi>A iuſt feare of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of our Ciuill Eſtate.</hi> So then, the <hi>War</hi> is not for the <hi>Palatinate</hi> onely, but for <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland, Ireland,</hi> our <hi>King,</hi> our <hi>Prince,</hi> our <hi>Nation,</hi> all that we haue. Wherein two things are to be proued. The one, that a <hi>iuſt Feare,</hi> (without an Actuall Inuaſion or Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,) is a ſufficient Ground of a <hi>War,</hi> and in the Nature of a true <hi>Defenſiue;</hi> The other, that wee haue towards <hi>Spaine</hi> Cauſe of <hi>iuſt Feare;</hi> I ſay <hi>iuſt Feare;</hi> For as the <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilians</hi>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:433:11"/> doe well define, that the Legall <hi>Feare</hi> is, <hi>Iuſtus Metus qui cadit in conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Virum,</hi> in priuate Cauſes; So there is, <hi>Iuſtus Metus qui cadit in conſtantem Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, in cauſa publica;</hi> Not out of vm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brages, light Iealouſies, Apprehenſions a farre off; But out of cleare Forefight of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Danger.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the former <hi>Propoſition,</hi> it is good to heare what time ſaith. <hi>Thucydides,</hi> in his <hi>Inducement</hi> to his Story of the great <hi>Warre</hi> of <hi>Peloponneſus,</hi> ſets downe in plaine termes, that the true Cauſe of that <hi>Warre</hi> was; <hi>The ouergrowing Greatneſſe of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians, and the feare that the Lacedemoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſtood in thereby;</hi> And doth not doubt to call it, <hi>A neceſsity impoſed vpon the Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonians of a Warre:</hi> Which are the Words of a meere <hi>Defenſiue:</hi> Adding, that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cauſes were but ſpecious and Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. <hi>Veriſsimam quidem, ſed minimè ſermone celebratam, arbitror extitiſſe Belli Cauſam, Athenienſes magnos effectos, &amp; Lacedemonijs formidoloſos, neceſsitatem illis impoſuiſſe Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landi: Quae autem propalam ferebantur
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:433:12"/> vtrinque Cauſae, iſtae fuerunt, &amp;c. The trueſt Cauſe of this Warre, though leaſt voyced, I conceiue to haue beene this; That the Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, being growne great, to the terrour of the Lacedemonians, did impoſe vpon them a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity of a Warre: But the Cauſes that went abroad in ſpeech were theſe, &amp;c. Sulpitius Galba,</hi> Conſul, when he perſwaded the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> to a Preuentiue <hi>Warre,</hi> with the latter <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon,</hi> in regard of the great Preparations which <hi>Philip</hi> had then on foot, and his Deſignes to ruine ſome of the Confederates of the <hi>Romans,</hi> confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaith; That they who tooke that for an <hi>Offenſius War,</hi> vnderſtood not the ſtate of the Queſtion. <hi>Ignorare videmini mihi, (Quirites,) non vtrum bellum an pacem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beatis, vos conſuli, (neque enim liberum id vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis permittet Philippus, qui terrâ marique in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens bellum molitur,) ſed vtrum in Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam legiones tranſportetis, an hoſtem in Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam recipiatis. Ye ſeeme to me (ye Romans,) not to vnderſtand, that the Conſultation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, is not, whether you ſhall haue Warre or Peace, (for Philip will take order you ſhall
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:433:12"/> be no chooſers, who prepareth a mighty Warre both by Land and Sea;) but whether you ſhall tranſport the Warre into Macedon, or receiue it into Italy. Antiochus,</hi> when he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited <hi>Pruſias</hi> King of <hi>Bithynia,</hi> (at that time in league with the <hi>Romans,</hi>) to ioyne with him in <hi>Warre</hi> againſt them, ſetteth before him, a iuſt Feare, of the ouerſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Greatneſſe of the <hi>Romans,</hi> comparing it to a Fire that continually tooke, and ſpread from Kingdome to Kingdome: <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire Romanos ad omnia Regna tollenda, vt nullum vſquam orbis terrarum niſi Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num imperium eſſet; Philippum &amp; Nabin ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnatos, ſe tertium peti; Vt quiſque proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ab oppreſſo ſit, per omnes velut continens incendium peruaſuru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. That the Romans came to pull downe all Kingdomes, and to make the State of Rome an vniuerſall Monarchie; That Philip and Nabis were already ruinated, and now was his turn to be aſſailed: So that as euery State lay next to the other that was oppreſſed, ſo the fire perpetually grazed.</hi> Wherein it is well to be noted, that towards ambitious States, (which are noted to aſpire to great
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:433:13"/> 
                     <hi>Monarchies,</hi> and to ſeeke vpon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to enlarge their Dominions,) <hi>Creſcunt Argumenta iuſti Metus:</hi> All particular feares doe grow and multiply out of the Contemplation of the generall Courſes and Practice of ſuch States. Therefore in Deliberations of <hi>Warre</hi> againſt the <hi>Turke,</hi> it hath beene often, with great iudgement, maintained; That <hi>Chriſtian Princes</hi> and <hi>States</hi> haue alwayes a ſufficient Ground of <hi>Inuaſiue Warre</hi> againſt the Enemie: Not for <hi>Cauſe</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> but vpon a iuſt <hi>Feare;</hi> Foraſmuch as it is a Fundamentall Law, in the <hi>Turkiſh Empire,</hi> that they may (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other prouocation,) make warre vpon <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> for the <hi>Propagation</hi> of their <hi>Law;</hi> So that there lieth vpon the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> a perpetuall <hi>Feare</hi> of a <hi>Warre,</hi> (hanging ouer their heads,) from them: And therefore, they may at all times, (as they thinke good,) be vpon the Preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> expoſeth to ſcorne <hi>Wars</hi> which are not Preuentiue, comparing thoſe that make them, to country Fellowes in a Fence Schoole, that neuer ward till the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:433:13"/> blow be paſt: <hi>Vt Barbari Pugiles dimicare ſolent, ita vos bellum geritis cum Philippo, Ex his enim is qui ictus eſt, ictui ſemper inhaeret: Quod ſi eum alibi verberes, illò manus tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert; Ictum autem depellere, aut proſpicere, neque ſcit, neque vult. As Country Fellowes vſe to doe when they play at Waſters, ſuch a kinde of warre doe you (Athenians) make with Philip; For with them hee that gets a blow, ſtreight falleth to ward when the blow is paſt; And if you ſtrike him in another place, thither goes his hand likewiſe: But to put by, or foreſee a blow, they neither haue the skill, northe will.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Clinias</hi> the <hi>Candian,</hi> (in <hi>Plato,</hi>) ſpeaks deſperately and wildly; As if there were no ſuch thing as <hi>Peace</hi> betweene <hi>Nations;</hi> But that euery <hi>Nation</hi> expects but his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage to Warre vpon another. But yet in that Exceſſe of Speech, there is thus much that may haue a ciuill Conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Namely, that euery State ought to ſtand vpon his guard, and rather preuent, than be preuented. His words are; <hi>Quam rem ferè vocant Pacem, nudum &amp; inane No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:433:14"/> eſt; Reuera autem omnibus, aduerſus omnes Ciuitates, bellum ſempiternum perdurat: That which Men, for the moſt part, call Peace, is but a naked and empty Name; But the truth is, that there is euer betweene all Eſtates a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Warre.</hi> I know well this Speech is the <hi>Obiection,</hi> and not the <hi>Deciſion,</hi> and that it is after refuted; But yet (as I ſaid before) it beares thus much of Truth; That if that generall Malignity, and Prediſpoſition to <hi>Warre,</hi> (which hee vntruly figureth to be in all Nations,) be produced and extended to a iuſt Feare of being oppreſſed, then it is no more a true <hi>Peace,</hi> but a Name of a <hi>Peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As for the Opinion of <hi>Iphicrates</hi> the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenian,</hi> it demands not ſo much towards a <hi>Warre,</hi> as a iuſt Feare; But rather commeth neare the Opinion of <hi>Clinias;</hi> As if there were euer amongſt Nations a Brooding of a <hi>War,</hi> and that there is no ſure League but Impuiſſance to doe hurt. For he, in the Treaty of Peace with the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> ſpeaketh plaine language; Telling them, there could be no true and ſecure Peace,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:433:14"/> except the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> yeelded to thoſe things, which being granted, it would be no longer in their power, to hurt the <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> though they would. And to ſay truth, if one marke it well, this was, in all Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, the maine peece of Wiſdome, in ſtrong and prudent Counſels; To bee in perpetuall watch, that the <hi>States</hi> about them, ſhould neither by Approach, nor by Encreaſe of Dominion, nor by Ruining Confederates, nor by blocking of Trade, nor by any the like meanes, haue it in their power, to hurt or annoy the <hi>States</hi> they ſerue; And whenſoeuer any ſuch Cauſe did but appeare, ſtraight-wayes to buy it out with a Warre, and neuer to take vp Peace at credit, and vpon Intereſt. It is ſo memorable, as it is yet as freſh, as if it were done yeſterday, how that <hi>Triumuirate</hi> of <hi>Kings, (Henry</hi> the eight of <hi>England, Francis</hi> the firſt of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, Emperour, and King of <hi>Spaine,</hi>) were in their times ſo prouident, as ſcarce a Palme of Ground could bee gotten by either of the Three, but that the other Two would
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:433:15"/> be ſure to doe their beſt, to ſet the Ballance of <hi>Europe</hi> vpright againe. And the like di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence was vſed in the Age before, by that League, (wherewith <hi>Guicciardine</hi> begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his Story, and maketh it (as it were) the Kalender of the good dayes of <hi>Italy,</hi>) which was contracted betweene <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nando</hi> King of <hi>Naples, Lorenzo of Medici</hi> Potentate of <hi>Florence,</hi> and <hi>Lodouico Zforza</hi> Duke of <hi>Milan,</hi> deſigned chiefly againſt the growing Power of the <hi>Venetians;</hi> But yet ſo, as the Confederates had a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all eye, one vpon another, that none of them ſhould ouertop. To conclude there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, howſoeuer ſome <hi>Schoolemen,</hi> (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Reuerend Men, yet fitter to guide Penkniues, than Swords,) ſeeme preciſely to ſtand vpon it; That euery <hi>Offenſiue Warre</hi> muſt be <hi>Vltio;</hi> A <hi>Reuenge,</hi> that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſeth a precedent Aſſault or Iniurie; yet neither doe they deſcend to this Point, (which we now handle,) of a <hi>iuſt Feare;</hi> Neither are they of authority to iudge this Queſtion againſt all the Preſidents of time. For certainly, as long as Men are Men, (the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:433:15"/> Sonnes, as the Poets allude, of <hi>Prometheus,</hi> and not of <hi>Epimetheus,</hi>) and as long as Reaſon is Reaſon; A <hi>iuſt Feare</hi> will be a iuſt Cauſe of a Preuentiue <hi>War;</hi> But eſpecially, if it be Part of the Caſe, that there be a <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> that is manifeſtly detected, to aſpire to <hi>Monarchie,</hi> and new Acqueſts; Then other <hi>States</hi> (aſſuredly) cannot be iuſtly accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, for not ſtaying for the firſt Blow; Or for not accepting <hi>Poliphemus</hi> Courteſie, to be the laſt that ſhall be eaten vp.</p>
                  <p>Nay I obſetue further, that in that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of <hi>Plato,</hi> which I cited before, (and euen in the <hi>Tenet</hi> of that Perſon, that bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the Reſoluing Part, and not the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecting part,) a <hi>iuſt Feare</hi> is iuſtified for a Cauſe of an <hi>Inuaſiue Warre,</hi> though the fame <hi>Feare</hi> proceed not, from the fault of the forraine State, to bee aſſailed. For it is there inſinuated; That if a State, out of the diſtemper of their owne Body, doe feare Sedition and inteſtine Troubles, to breake out amongſt themſelues, they may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge their owne ill Humours, vpon a forraine <hi>Warre,</hi> for a Cure. And this kind
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:433:16"/> of Cure, was tendred by <hi>Iaſper Coligni Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> to <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth, the <hi>French King,</hi> when by a viue and forcible perſwaſion, he moued him to a warre vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Flanders,</hi> for the better Extinguiſhment of the <hi>Ciuill Warres</hi> of <hi>France;</hi> But neither was that Counſell proſperous; Neither will I maintaine that Poſition; For I will neuer ſet <hi>Politiques</hi> againſt <hi>Ethicks;</hi> Eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for that true <hi>Ethicks</hi> are but as a Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid to <hi>Diuinity</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi> Surely, Saint <hi>Thomas,</hi> (who had the largeſt heart of the <hi>Schoole Diuines,</hi>) bendeth chiefly his ſtile againſt the depraued Paſſions, which reigne in making <hi>Warres,</hi> ſpeaking out of S. <hi>Auguſtine; Nocendi Cupiditas, vlciſcendi Crudelitas, implacatus &amp; implacabilis Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Feritas Rebellandi, Libido Dominandi, &amp; ſi quae ſunt ſimilia, haec ſunt quae in Bellis iure culpantur.</hi> And the ſame <hi>Saint Thomas,</hi> in his owne Text, defining of the iuſt Cauſes of a <hi>Warre,</hi> doth leaue it vpon very generall Tearmes; <hi>Requiritur ad Bellum Cauſa iuſta, vt ſcilicet illi qui impugnantur, propter aliquam culpam, Impugnationem me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reantur;</hi>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:433:16"/> For <hi>Impugnatio Culpae,</hi> is a farre more generall word, than <hi>vltio Iniuriae.</hi> thus much for the firſt <hi>Propoſition,</hi> of the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Ground</hi> of a <hi>War</hi> with <hi>Spaine:</hi> Namely, that a <hi>iuſt Feare is a iuſt Cauſe of a War</hi> And that a <hi>Preuentiue Warre is a true Defenſiue.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Second or <hi>Minor Propoſition</hi> was this; That this <hi>Kingdome</hi> hath Cauſe of <hi>iuſt Feare</hi> of Ouerthrow from <hi>Spaine.</hi> Wherein it is true, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Feares</hi> are euer ſeene in dimmer lights, than <hi>Facts.</hi> And on the other ſide, <hi>Feares</hi> vſe (many times) to be repreſented in ſuch an Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary faſhion, as they rather dazell Mens eyes, than open them. And therefore I will ſpeake in that manner, which the Subiect requires; That is, probably, and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, and briefly. Neither will I deduce th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe <hi>Feares</hi> to preſent Occurrences; but point only at generall Grounds, leauing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he reſt to more ſecret Counſels.</p>
                  <p>Is it nothing, that the <hi>Crowne</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> hath enlarged the Bounds thereof, within this laſt ſixſcore yeares, much more than the <hi>Ottomans?</hi> I ſpeake not of Matches, or
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:433:17"/> Vnions, but of Armes, Occupations, Inuaſions. <hi>Granada, Naples, Milan, Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal,</hi> the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt Indies;</hi> All theſe are actuall Additions to that <hi>Crowne.</hi> They had a mind to <hi>French Britaine,</hi> the lower Part of <hi>Piccardi,</hi> and <hi>Piemont;</hi> but they haue let fall their Bit. They haue, at this day, ſuch a houering poſſeſſion of the <hi>Valtoline,</hi> as an Hobby hath ouer a Larke: And the <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate</hi> is in their Tallons: So that nothing is more manifeſt, than that this <hi>Nation</hi> of <hi>Spaine</hi> runnes a race (ſtill) of <hi>Empire;</hi> When all other <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> ſtand in effect at a ſtay. Looke then a little fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, into the Titles, whereby they haue acquired, and doe now hold theſe new Portions of their <hi>Crowne,</hi> and you will finde them of ſo many varieties, and ſuch natures, (to ſpeake with due reſpect,) as may appeare to be eaſily minted, and ſuch as can hardly at any time be wanting. And therefore, ſo many new Conqueſts &amp; Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſes, ſo many Strokes of the Larum Bell of <hi>Feare,</hi> and Awaking, to other <hi>Nations.</hi> And the Facility of the Titles, which hand
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:433:17"/> ouerhead haue ſerued their turne, doth ring the Peale ſo much the ſharper, and the lowder.</p>
                  <p>Shall wee deſcend from their generall Diſpoſition, to inlarge their Dominions, to their particular Diſpoſition, and Eye of Appetite, which they haue had towards vs; They haue now twice ſought to impatroniſe themſelues of this <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> once by <hi>Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age</hi> with <hi>Queene Mary;</hi> And the ſecond time by <hi>Conqueſt</hi> in 88. when their Forces by Sea and Land, were not inferiour to thoſe they haue now. And at that time in 88. the Counſell and Deſigne of <hi>Spaine,</hi> was, by many aduertiſements, reuealed and laid open to bee; That they found the <hi>Warre</hi> vpon the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> ſo churliſh and longſome, as they grew then to a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution; That as long as <hi>England</hi> ſtood in ſtate to ſuccour thoſe <hi>Countries,</hi> they ſhould but conſume themſelues in an end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe <hi>Warre;</hi> And therefore there was no other way, but to aſſaile and depreſſe <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which was as a Backe of Steele to the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:433:18"/> 
                     <hi>Flemmings.</hi> And who can warrant (I pray) that the ſame Counſell and Deſigne will not returne againe? So as we are in a ſtrange <hi>Dilemma</hi> of Danger: For if wee ſuffer the <hi>Flemmings</hi> to be ruined, they are our Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke, and wee ſhall remaine Naked and Diſmantled: If wee ſuccour them ſtrongly, (as is fit,) and ſet them vpon their feet, and doe not withall weaken <hi>Spaine,</hi> we hazard to change the Scene of the <hi>War,</hi> and to turne it vpon <hi>Ireland,</hi> or <hi>England:</hi> Like vnto <hi>Rheumes</hi> and <hi>Defluxions;</hi> which, if you apply a ſtrong Repercuſſiue to the Place affected, and doe not take away the Cauſe of the Diſeaſe, will ſhift, and fall ſtraightwayes to another Ioynt, or Place. They haue alſo twice inuaded <hi>Ireland<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> Once vnder the <hi>Popes Banner,</hi> when they were defeated by the Lo. <hi>Grey;</hi> And after in their owne name, when they were defeated by the Lo. <hi>Mountioy.</hi> So as let this ſuffice for a Taſte of their Diſpoſition to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs. But it will be ſaid: This is an Almanacke for the old yeare: Since 88. all hath beene well; <hi>Spaine</hi> hath not aſſailed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:433:18"/> this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> howſoeuer by two ſeuerall Inuaſions from vs mightily prouoked. It is true, but then conſider; that immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after 88. they were imbroyled, for a great time, in the Protection of the Leagu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of <hi>France,</hi> whereby they had their hands full; After being brought extreme low, by their vaſt and continuall Embracements, they were enforced to be quiet, that they might take Breath, and doe Reparations vpon their former Waſtes. But now of late Things ſeeme to come on apace to their former Eſtate. Nay with farre greater Diſaduantage to vs. For now that they haue almoſt continued, and (as it were,) arched, their Dominions, from <hi>Milan,</hi> by the <hi>Valtoline,</hi> and <hi>Palatinate,</hi> to the <hi>Low-Countries;</hi> We ſee how they thirſt and pant after the vtter Ruine of thoſe <hi>States;</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in contempt almoſt the <hi>German Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and doubting little oppoſition except it come from <hi>England:</hi> Whereby either we muſt ſuffer the <hi>Dutch</hi> to be ruined, to our owne manifeſt preiudice; Or put it vpon the hazard, I ſpake of before, that <hi>Spaine</hi>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:433:19"/> will caſt at the faireſt. Neither is the point of <hi>Internall Danger,</hi> which groweth vpon vs, to be forgotten; This; That the Party of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in <hi>England</hi> are become more knotted, both in Dependance towards <hi>Spaine,</hi> and amongſt themſelues, than they haue beene. Wherein againe comes to be remembred the Caſe of 88: For then alſo it appeared, by diuers ſecret letters, that the Deſigne of <hi>Spaine</hi> was, (for ſome yeares before the inuaſion attempted,) to prepare a Party in this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> to adhere to the <hi>Forrainer</hi> at his comming. And they brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, that they doubted not, but to abuſe and lay aſleepe the <hi>Queene</hi> and <hi>Counſell</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> as to haue any feare of the Party of <hi>Papiſts</hi> here; For that they knew (they ſaid) the <hi>State</hi> would but caſt the eye, and looke about, to ſee whether there were any Eminent Head of that Party, vnder whom it might vnite it ſelfe; And finding none worth the thinking on, the <hi>State</hi> would reſt ſecure, and take no apprehenſion; Whereas they meant, (they ſaid,) to take a courſe, to deale with the People, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:433:19"/> by Reconcilements, and Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Secret Promiſes, and cared not for any Head of Party. And this was the true reaſon, why after that the <hi>Seminaries</hi> beganne to bloſſome, and to make Miſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons into <hi>England,</hi> (which was about the three and twentieth yeare of <hi>Queene Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> at what time alſo was the firſt ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Spaniſh Inuaſion,</hi>) then, and not before, grew the ſharpe and ſeuere Lawes, to be made againſt the Papiſts. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Papiſts</hi> may doe well, to change their thanks; And whereas they thanke <hi>Spaine</hi> for their Fauours, to thanke them for their Perills and Miſeries, if they ſhould fall vpon them: For that nothing euer made their Caſe ſo ill, as the Doubt of the Greatneſſe of <hi>Spaine;</hi> which adding Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>State,</hi> to Matter of Conſcience and Religion, did whet the <hi>Lawes</hi> againſt them. And this Caſe alſo ſeemeth (in ſome ſort) to returne againe at this time; except the Clemencie of his <hi>Maieſty,</hi> and the <hi>State,</hi> doe ſuperabound: As, for my part, I doe wiſh it ſhould; And that the Proceedings
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:433:20"/> towards them, may rather tend to Security, and Prouidence, and Point of State, than to Perſecution for Religion. But to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude; Theſe Things briefly touched, may ſerue, as in a Subiect Coniecturall, and Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for to repreſent, how iuſt Cauſe of <hi>Feare,</hi> this <hi>Kingdome</hi> may haue towards <hi>Spaine:</hi> Omitting (as I ſaid before,) all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and more ſecret Occurrences.</p>
                  <p>The third Ground of a <hi>Warre</hi> with <hi>Spaine,</hi> I haue ſet downe to be; <hi>A iuſt Feare of the Subuerſion of our Church and Religion.</hi> Which needeth little Speech: For if this <hi>Warre</hi> be a <hi>Defenſiue,</hi> (as I haue proued it to be,) no Man will doubt; That a <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue Warre,</hi> againſt a Forrainer, for <hi>Religion,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s lawfull. Of an <hi>Offenſiue Warre</hi> there is more Diſpute: And yet in that inſtance of the <hi>Warre</hi> for the <hi>Holy Land,</hi> and <hi>Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher,</hi> I doe wonder ſometimes, that the <hi>Schoole Men</hi> want words to defend that, which S. <hi>Bernard</hi> wanted words to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend. But I, that in this little Extract of a Treatiſe, doe omit things neceſſary, am
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:433:20"/> not to handle things vnneceſſary. No man, I ſay, will doubt, but if the <hi>Pope,</hi> or <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> would demand of vs to forſake our <hi>Religion,</hi> vpon paine of a <hi>Warre,</hi> it were as vniuſt a Demand, as the <hi>Perſians</hi> made to the <hi>Grecians</hi> of <hi>Land</hi> and <hi>Water;</hi> Or the <hi>Ammonites</hi> to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> of their <hi>Right Eies.</hi> And we ſee all the <hi>Heathen</hi> did ſtile their <hi>Defenſiue Wars, Pro Aris &amp; Focis;</hi> Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing their Altars, before their Hearths. So that it is in vaine of this to ſpeake further. Onely this is true; That the <hi>Feare</hi> of the <hi>Subuerſion</hi> of our <hi>Religion</hi> from <hi>Spaine,</hi> is the more iuſt, for that all other <hi>Catholique Princes</hi> and <hi>States,</hi> content and containe themſelues, to maintaine their <hi>Religion</hi> within their owne Dominions, and med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle not with the Subiects of other <hi>States;</hi> Whereas the Practice of <hi>Spaine</hi> hath beene, both in <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth's time, and in the time of the <hi>League</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> by <hi>Warre;</hi> And now with vs, by Conditions of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to intermeddle with <hi>Forraine States,</hi> and to declare themſelues Protectors gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, of the Party of <hi>Catholiques,</hi> through
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:433:21"/> the World. As if the Crowne of <hi>Spaine</hi> had a little of this; That they would plant the <hi>Popes Law</hi> by Armes, as the <hi>Ottomans</hi> doe the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Mahomet.</hi> Thus much concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the firſt maine point of <hi>Iuſtifying the Quarrell,</hi> if the <hi>King</hi> ſhall enter into a <hi>War;</hi> For this that I haue ſaid, and all that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth to be ſaid, is but to ſhew what he may doe.</p>
                  <p>The Second maine Part, of that I haue propounded to ſpeake of, is the <hi>Ballance of Forces betweene Spaine and vs.</hi> And this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo tendeth to no more, but what the <hi>King</hi> may doe. For <hi>what hee may doe,</hi> is of two kinds: What hee may doe as <hi>Iuſt;</hi> And what he may doe as <hi>Poſsible.</hi> Of the one I haue already ſpoken; Of the other I am now to ſpeake. I ſaid, <hi>Spaine</hi> was no ſuch <hi>Giant;</hi> And yet if he were a <hi>Giant,</hi> it will be, but as it was betweene <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah;</hi> for <hi>God is on our ſide.</hi> But to leaue all Arguments that are Supernaturall, and to ſpeake in an Humane and Politique Senſe; I am led to thinke that <hi>Spaine</hi> is no ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>match
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:433:21"/> for <hi>England,</hi> by that which leadeth all Men; That is, <hi>Experience,</hi> and <hi>Reaſon.</hi> And with <hi>Experience</hi> I will beginne; For there all <hi>Reaſon</hi> beginneth.</p>
                  <p>Is it Fortune, (ſhall we thinke,) that in all Actions of <hi>Warre</hi> or Armes, great and ſmall, which haue happened theſe many yeares, euer ſince <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>England</hi> haue had any thing to debate, one with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> vpon all Encounters, haue perpetually come off with honour, and the better? It is not Fortune ſure; Shee is not ſo conſtant. There is ſomewhat in the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and Naturall Courage of the People, or ſome ſuch thing. I will make a briefe Liſt of the Particulars themſelues, in an Hiſtoricall Truth, no wayes ſtrowted, nor made greater by Language. This were a fit Speech, (you will ſay,) for a <hi>Generall,</hi> in the Head of an Army, when they were go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Battell; Yes; And it is no leſſe fit Speech, to bee ſpoken, in the Head of a Counſell, vpon a Deliberation of Entrance into a <hi>Warre.</hi> Neither ſpeake I this to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parage the <hi>Spaniſh Nation,</hi> whom I take to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:433:22"/> be of the beſt Souldiers in <hi>Europe.</hi> But that ſorteth to our honour, if wee ſtill haue had the better hand.</p>
                  <p>In the yeare 1578. was that famous <hi>Lammas Day,</hi> which buried the Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Don Ihuan d' Auſtrià,</hi> himſelfe not ſuruiuing long after. <hi>Don Ihuan,</hi> being ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour in Forces, aſſiſted by the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Parma, Mondragon, Manſell,</hi> and other the beſt Commanders of <hi>Spaine,</hi> confident of Victory, charged the Army of the <hi>States,</hi> neere <hi>Rimenant,</hi> brauely &amp; furiouſly at the firſt; But after a Fight, maintained by the ſpace of a whole day, was repulſed, and forced to a Retrait, with great ſlaughter of his Men; And the Courſe of his further Enterprizes was wholly arreſted; And this chiefly by the Proweſſe and Vertue of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Troupes, vnder the Conduct of Sir <hi>Iohn Norris,</hi> and Sir <hi>Robert Stuart,</hi> Colonels. Which Troupes came to the Army but the day before, harraſed with a long and weariſome march: and (as it is left for a memorable circumſtance in all Stories,) the Souldiers, being more ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:433:22"/> of a little Heat of the Sunne, than of any cold Feare of Death, caſt away their Armour, and Garments from them, and fought in their Shirts: And, as it was gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally conceiued, had it not beene, that the <hi>Count</hi> of <hi>Boſſu</hi> was ſlacke, in charging the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> vpon their Retreit, this Fight had ſorted to an abſolute Defeat. But it was enough, to chaſtiſe <hi>Don Ihuan,</hi> for his inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Treaty of Peace, wherewith he had abuſed the <hi>States</hi> at his firſt comming. And the Fortune of the day, (beſides the teſtimonie of all Stories,) may be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter aſcribed to the Seruice of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scottiſh,</hi> by compariſon of this Charge neare <hi>Rimenant,</hi> (where the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scottiſh,</hi> in great numbers, came in action,) with the like Charge giuen by <hi>Don Ihuan,</hi> halfe a yeare before at <hi>Gemblours,</hi> where the Succeſſe was contrary: There being at that time, in the Army, but a Handfull of <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scottiſh,</hi> and they put in diſarray, by the Horſemen, of their owne Fellowes.</p>
                  <p>The firſt Dart of <hi>Warre,</hi> which was
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:433:23"/> throwne from <hi>Spaine,</hi> or <hi>Rome,</hi> vpon the Realme of <hi>Ireland,</hi> was in the yeare 1580 For the Deſigne of <hi>Stukeley</hi> blew ouer into <hi>Africke;</hi> And the Attempt of <hi>Sanders,</hi> and <hi>Fitz-Maurice,</hi> had a ſpice of Madneſſe. In that yeare, <hi>Ireland</hi> was inuaded by <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> and <hi>Italian</hi> Forces, vnder the <hi>Popes</hi> Banner, and the Conduct of <hi>Sant Ioſepho,</hi> to the number of 700. or better, which landed at <hi>Smerwicke</hi> in <hi>Kerey.</hi> A poore Number it was, to conquer <hi>Ireland,</hi> to the <hi>Popes</hi> vſe; For their Deſigne was no leſſe: But withall they brought Armes for 5000. Men aboue their owne company, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to arme ſo many of the <hi>Rebels</hi> of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> And their purpoſe was, to fortifie in ſome ſtrong Place of the wilde and Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Country, and there to neſtle till grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Succours came; They being haſtened vnto this Enterpriſe, vpon a ſpeciall Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of State, not proper to the Enterpriſe it ſelfe; Which was, by the Inuaſion of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Noyſe thereof, to trouble the <hi>Counſell</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and to make a diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of certaine Aids, that then were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:433:23"/> from hence, for the <hi>Low Countries.</hi> They choſe a place, where they erected a <hi>Fort,</hi> which they called the <hi>Fort del Or<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> And from thence they bolted like Beaſts of the Forreſt, ſometimes into the Woods and Faſtneſſes, and ſometimes backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to their Den. Soone after Siege was laid to the <hi>Fort,</hi> by the Lord <hi>Gray,</hi> then De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty, with a ſmaller Number than thoſe were within the <hi>Fort;</hi> Venturouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; But haſte was made to attache them before the <hi>Rebels</hi> came in to them. After the ſiege of foure dayes only, and two or three Sallies, with loſſe on their part, they that ſhould haue made good the <hi>Fort</hi> for ſome moneths, till new Succours came from <hi>Spaine,</hi> or at leaſt from the Rebels of <hi>Ireland,</hi> yeelded vp themſelues, without conditions, at the end of thoſe foure daies. And for that there were not in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army enough to keepe euery man a Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; And for that alſo the <hi>Deputy</hi> expected inſtantly to be aſſailed by the Rebels; And againe, there were no Barks to throw them into, and ſend them away by Sea; They
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:433:24"/> were all put to the ſword: With which <hi>Queene Elizabeth</hi> was afterwards much diſpleaſed.</p>
                  <p>In the yeare 1582. was that Memorable <hi>Retreit</hi> of <hi>Gaunt;</hi> Than the which there hath not beene an Exploit of <hi>Warre</hi> more celebrated. For in the true iudgement of Men of <hi>Warre,</hi> honourable Retreits are no wayes inferiour to braue Charges; As ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing leſſe of Fortune, more of Diſcipline, and as much of Valour. There were to the number of 300. Horſe, and as many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Foot <hi>Engliſh,</hi> (commanded by Sir <hi>Iohn Norris,</hi>) charged by the Prince of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> comming vpon them with 7000. Horſe; Beſides that the whole Army of <hi>Spaniards</hi> was ready to march on. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe Sir <hi>Iohn Norris</hi> maintained a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treit</hi> without Diſarray, by the ſpace of ſome miles, (part of the way champagne,) vnto the City of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> with leſſe loſſe of Men than the Enemy: The D. of <hi>Aniou,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Aurange,</hi> beholding this noble Action, from the <hi>Wals</hi> of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> as in a Theatre, with great Admiration.</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:433:24"/>
                  <p>In the yeare 1585. followed the Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Expedition</hi> of <hi>Drake,</hi> and <hi>Carlile,</hi> into the <hi>Weſt Indies.</hi> In the which, I ſet a ſide the Taking of <hi>S. Iago,</hi> and <hi>S. Domingo</hi> in <hi>Hiſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niola,</hi> as Surpriſes, rather than Encounters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But that of <hi>Catargena,</hi> where the <hi>Spaniards</hi> had warning of our comming, &amp; had put themſelues in their full ſtrength, was one of the hotteſt Seruices, &amp; moſt dangerous Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults, that hath bin known. For the Acceſſe to the Town, was only by a Neck of Land, betweene the Sea on the one part, and the Harbour Water or Inner Sea on the other; Fortified cleane ouer with a ſtrong Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier and Barracado; So as vpon the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent of our Men, they had both great Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and ſmall Shot, that thundred and ſhowred vpon them, from the Rampier in front, and from the Gallies that lay at Sea in flanke. And yet they forced the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and wan the Towne, being likewiſe very well manned. As for the Expedition of Sir <hi>Francis Drake,</hi> in the yeare 1587. for the deſtroying of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Shipping, and Prouiſion vpon their owne Coaſt;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:433:25"/> As I cannot ſay, that there interuened in that Enterpriſe, any ſharpe Fight or En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter; So neuertheleſſe, it did ſtrangely diſcouer, either that <hi>Spaine</hi> is very weake at home, or very ſlow to moue; When they ſuffered a ſmall Fleet of <hi>Engliſh,</hi> to make an hoſtile Inuaſion, or Incurſion, vpon their Hauens and Roads, from <hi>Cadez</hi> to <hi>Capa Sacra,</hi> and thence to <hi>Caſcais;</hi> And to fire, ſinke, and carry away, at the leaſt, 10000. tonne of their great Shipping, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides 50. or 60. of their ſmaller Veſſels: And that in the ſight, and vnder the Fauour of their <hi>Forts;</hi> And almoſt vnder the Eye of their great <hi>Admirall,</hi> (the beſt <hi>Commander</hi> of <hi>Spaine</hi> by Sea,) the <hi>Marquis de Santa Cruz,</hi> without euer being diſputed with, by any fight of importance. I remember <hi>Drake,</hi> in the vaunting ſtile of a Souldier, would call this Enterpriſe; <hi>The C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ngeing of the King of Spaines Beard.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Enterpriſe of 88. deſerueth to bee ſtood vpon a little more fully, being a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of Time. There armed from <hi>Spaine,</hi> in the yeare 1588. the greateſt <hi>Nauy</hi> that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:433:25"/> euer ſwam vpon the Sea. For though there haue beene farre greater Fleets for Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, yet for the Bulke and Building of the Ships, with the Furniture of great Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and Prouiſions, neuer the like. The Deſigne was to make, not an Inuaſion on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but an vtter Conqueſt of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. The Number of Veſſels were 130. whereof Galliaſſes and Gallions 72, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ships, like floating Towers, or Caſtles, manned with 30000. Souldiers, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners. This <hi>Nauy</hi> was the Preparation of fiue whole yeares at the leaſt. It bare it ſelfe alſo vpon Diuine Aſſiſtance; For it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued ſpeciall Bleſſing from <hi>Pope Ziſtus,</hi> and was aſſigned as an <hi>Apoſtolicall Miſsion,</hi> for the reducement of this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> to the obedience of the <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> And in further token of this holy Warfare, there were amongſt the reſt of theſe Ships, Twelue, called by the names of the <hi>Twelue Apoſtles.</hi> But it was truly conceiued, that this Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> could neuer be ouer-whelmed, except the Land-Waters came in to the Sea-Tides. Therefore was
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:433:26"/> there alſo in readineſſe, in <hi>Flanders,</hi> a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſtrong Army of Land-Forces, to the number of 50000. veterane Souldiers, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Conduct of the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Parma,</hi> the beſt Commander, next the <hi>French King Henrie</hi> the fourth, of his time. Theſe were deſigned to ioyne with the forces at Sea; There being prepared a Number of flat bottomed boats, to tranſport the Land-Forces, vnder the Wing and Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Great <hi>Nauy.</hi> For they made no account, but that the <hi>Nauy</hi> ſhould be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely Maſter of the Seas. Againſt theſe Forces, there were prepared, on our part, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o the number of neare 100. Ships; Not ſo great of Bulke indeed, but of a more nimble Motion, and more ſeruiceable; Beſides a leſſe Fleet of 30. Ships, for the Cuſtody of the Narrow Seas. There were alſo in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, at Land, two Armies; beſides other Forces, to the number of 10000, diſperſed amongſt the Coaſt Townes, in the Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne Parts. The two Armies were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed; One of them conſiſting of 25000. Horſe and Foot, for the Repulſing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:433:26"/> of the Enemy, at their landing; And the other of 25000. for ſafeguard and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance about the Court, and the <hi>Queenes</hi> Perſon. There were alſo other Dormant Muſters of Souldiers, thorowout all Parts of the Realme, that were put in readineſſe, but not drawne together. The two Armies were aſſigned to the Leading of two Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, Noble Perſons, but both of them, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Courtiers, and Aſſured to the State, than Martiall Men; yet lined and aſſiſted with Subordinate Commanders, of great Experience, &amp; Valour. The Fortune of the <hi>Warre</hi> made this enterpriſe, at firſt, a Play at Baſe. The <hi>Spaniſh Nauy</hi> ſet forth out of the <hi>Groyne</hi> in <hi>May,</hi> and was diſperſed and driuen backe by Weather. Our <hi>Nauy</hi> ſet forth ſomewhat later out of <hi>Plimouth,</hi> and bare vp towards the Coaſt of <hi>Spaine,</hi> to haue fought with the <hi>Spaniſh Nauy;</hi> And partly by reaſon of contrary Winds, partly vpon aduertiſement that the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> were gone backe, and vpon ſome doubt alſo that they might paſſe by to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Coaſt of <hi>England,</hi> whileſt wee
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:433:27"/> were ſeeking them a farre off, returned likewiſe into <hi>Plimouth,</hi> about the Middle of <hi>Iuly.</hi> At that time, came more confident Aduertiſement, (though falſe,) not only to the Lord <hi>Admirall,</hi> but to the <hi>Court,</hi> that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> could not poſſibly come for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward that yeare; Whereupon our <hi>Nauy</hi> was vpon the point of disbanding, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our Men gone aſhore. At which ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time, the <hi>Inuincible Armada,</hi> (for ſo it was called in a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> oſtentation thorowout <hi>Europe,</hi>) was diſcouered vpon the Weſterne Coaſt. It was a kinde of Surpriſe; For that (as was ſaid,) many of our Men were gone to Land, and our Ships ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part. Neuertheleſſe the Admirall, with ſuch Ships only as could ſuddenly bee put in readineſſe, made forth towards them: In ſomuch as of 100. Ships, there came ſcarce thirty to worke. Howbeit with them, and ſuch as came dayly in, we ſet vpon them, and gaue them the chaſe. But the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> for want of Courage, (which they called <hi>Commiſsion,</hi>) declined the Fight, caſting themſelues continually into Roun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:433:27"/> (their ſtrongeſt Ships walling in the reſt,) and in that manner they made a fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing march towards <hi>Callis.</hi> Our Men, by the ſpace of fiue or ſix dayes, followed them cloſe, fought with them continually, made great Slaughter of their Men, tooke two of their great Ships, and gaue diuers others of their Ships their Deaths wounds, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſoone after they ſanke and periſhed, And (in a word) diſtreſſed them almoſt in the nature of a Defeat; We our ſelues, in the meane time, receiuing little or no hurt. Neere <hi>Callis</hi> the <hi>Spaniards</hi> anchored, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting their Land-forces, which came not. It was afterwards alledged, that the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Parma</hi> did artificially delay his Comming: But this was, but an Inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Pretenſion giuen out by the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards;</hi> Partly vpon a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Enuie againſt that <hi>Duke,</hi> being an <hi>Italian,</hi> and his Sonne a Competitor to <hi>Portugall;</hi> But chiefly, to ſaue the Monſtrous Scorne and Diſreputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which they and their Nation recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, by the Succeſſe of that Enterpriſe. Therefore their Colours and Excuſes (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth)
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:433:28"/> were, that their Generall by Sea had a limitted Commiſſion, not to fight vntill the Land-forces were come in to them: And that the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Parma</hi> had particular Reaches, and Ends of his owne, vnderhand, to croſſe the Deſigne. But it was both a ſtrange Commiſſion, and a ſtrange obedience to a Commiſſion, for Men in the middeſt of their owne Bloud, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo furiouſly aſſailed, to hold their hands, contrary to the Lawes of Nature and Neceſſity. And as for the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> he was reaſonably well tempted to be true to that Enterpriſe, by no leſſe Promiſe, than to be made a Feudatary, or Benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> vnder the Seignorie (in chiefe) of the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the Protection of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spaine.</hi> Beſides it appeared, that the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Parma</hi> held his place long after, in the Fauour and Truſt of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> by the great Employments and Seruices that he performed in <hi>France:</hi> And againe, it is manifeſt, that the <hi>Duke</hi> did his beſt to come downe, and to put to Sea: The Truth was, that the <hi>Spaniſh
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:433:28"/> Nauy,</hi> vpon thoſe proofes of Fight, which they had with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> finding how much hurt they receiued, and how little hurt they did, by reaſon of the Actiuity and low building of our Ships, and skill of our Sea-men; And being alſo comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by a Generall of ſmall Courage and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience; And hauing loſt, at the firſt, two of their braueſt Commanders at Sea, <hi>Petro de Valdez,</hi> and <hi>Michael de Oquenda;</hi> durſt not put it to a Battell at Sea, but ſet vp their reſt wholly vpon the Land-Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe. On the other ſide, the Tranſporting of the Land-forces failed in the very Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. For whereas the <hi>Counſell</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> made full account, that their <hi>Nauy</hi> ſhould be Maſter of the Sea, and therefore able to guard and protect the Veſſels of Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation; When it fell out to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that the Great <hi>Nauy</hi> was diſtreſſed, and had enough to doe to ſaue it ſelfe; And againe that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> impounded their Land-forces, with a braue Fleet of 30. Saile, excellently well appointed; Things (I ſay) being in this State, it came
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:433:29"/> to paſſe, that the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Parma</hi> muſt haue flowne, if he would haue come into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> for hee could get neither Barke nor Mariner to put to Sea: Yet certaine it is, that the <hi>Duke</hi> looked ſtill for the comming backe of the <hi>Armada,</hi> euen at that time, when they were wandring, and making their Perambulation vpon the Northerne Seas. But to returne to the <hi>Armada,</hi> which we left anchored at <hi>Callis.</hi> From thence, (as Sir <hi>Walter Rawlegh</hi> was wont prettily to ſay,) <hi>they were ſuddenly driuen away with Squibs;</hi> For it was no more, but a Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem of Fire-boats, Manleſſe, and ſent vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them by the fauour of the Wind, in the night time, that did put them in ſuch ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, as they cut their Cables, and left their Anchors in the Sea. After they houered ſome 2 or 3 daies about <hi>Graueling,</hi> &amp; there againe were beaten in a great Fight, at what time our ſecond Fleet, which kept the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Seas, was come in, and ioyned to our maine Fleet. Thereupon the <hi>Spaniards</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into further terrour, and finding alſo diuers of their Ships euery day to ſinke,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:433:29"/> loſt all courage, &amp; in ſtead of comming vp into the <hi>Thames Mouth</hi> for <hi>London,</hi> (as their Deſigne was,) fled on towards the <hi>North,</hi> to ſeeke their Fortunes; Being ſtill chaced by the <hi>Engliſh Nauy</hi> at the heeles; vntill we were faine to giue them ouer for want of Powder. The Breath of <hi>Scotland</hi> the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> could not endure; Neither durſt they as Inuaders land in <hi>Ireland;</hi> But only ennobled ſome of the Coaſts thereof with ſhipwracks. And ſo going Northwards aloofe, as long as they had any doubt of being purſued, at laſt when they were out of reach, they turned, and croſſed the Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an to <hi>Spaine,</hi> hauing loſt foureſcore of their Ships, and the greater part of their Men. And this was the End of that <hi>Sea-Giant,</hi> the <hi>Inuincible Armada.</hi> Which hauing not ſo much as fired a Cottage of ours at Land, nor taken a Cockboat of ours at Sea, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered thorow the Wilderneſſe of the Northerne Seas; And according to the Curſe in the Scripture; <hi>Came out againſt vs one way, and fled before vs ſeuen wayes.</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing only to make good the iudgement of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:433:30"/> an <hi>Aſtrologer,</hi> long before giuen; <hi>Octuage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimus octauus Mirabilis Annus;</hi> Or rather, to make good, (euen to the aſtoniſhment of all Poſterity,) the wonderfull Iudgements of God, powred downe, commonly, vpon vaſt, and proud Aſpirings.</p>
                  <p>In the yeare, that followed, of 1589. we gaue the <hi>Spaniards</hi> no breath, but tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Challengers, and inuaded the Maine of <hi>Spaine.</hi> In which Enterpriſe, although we failed of our End, which was to ſettle <hi>Don Antonio</hi> in the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Portugall,</hi> yet a Man ſhall hardly meet with an Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that doth better reueale the great Secret of the Power of <hi>Spaine:</hi> Which Power, well ſought into, will be found, rather to conſiſt in a Veterane Army, (ſuch as vpon ſeuerall Occaſions and Pretenſions, they haue euer had on foot, in one part or other of <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> now by the ſpace of (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt) ſix ſcore yeares,) than in the ſtrength of their Dominions, and Prouinces. For what can be more ſtrange, or more to the Diſualuation of the Power of the <hi>Spaniard</hi> vpon the Continent, than that with an
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:433:30"/> Army of a 11000. <hi>Engliſh,</hi> Land Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and a Fleet of 26. Ships of warre, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides ſome weake Veſſells for Tranſportati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we ſhould within the Houre-glaſſe of two moneths, haue wonne one Towne of importance by <hi>Eſcalada;</hi> Battered and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted another; Querthrowne great Forces in the Field, &amp; that vpon the diſaduantage of a Bridge ſtrongly barracadoed, Landed the Army in three ſeuerall Places of his <hi>Kingdome;</hi> Marched ſeuen dayes in the Heart of his Countries; Lodged three nights in the Suburbs of his principall Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; Beaten his Forces into the Gates there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; Poſſeſſed two of his Frontire Forts; And come off, after all this, with ſmall loſſe of Men, otherwiſe than by Sickneſſe. And it was verily thought, that had it not beene for foure great Disfauours of that Voyage; (That is to ſay; The failing in ſundry Prouiſions that were promiſed, eſpecially of Cannons for Battery; The vaine Hopes of <hi>Don Antonio</hi> concerning the People of the Country, to come in to his aid; The Diſappointment of the Fleet
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:433:31"/> that was directed to come vp the <hi>Riuer</hi> of <hi>Lisbone;</hi> And laſtly, the Diſeaſes which ſpred in the Army, by reaſon of the Heat of the Seaſon, and of the Souldiers Miſrule in Diet;) the Enterpriſe had ſucceeded, and <hi>Lisbone</hi> had beene carried. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, it makes proofe to the World, that an Inuaſion of a few <hi>Engliſh</hi> vpon <hi>Spaine,</hi> may haue iuſt hope of Victory, at leaſt of Paſport to depart ſafely.</p>
                  <p>In the yeare 1591. was that Memorable Fight, of an <hi>Engliſh Ship</hi> called the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge,</hi> vnder the Command of Sir <hi>Richard Greenuill;</hi> Memorable (I ſay) euen beyond credit, and to the Height of ſome Heroicall Fable. And though it were a Defeat, yet it exceeded a Victory; Being like the Act of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> that killed more Men at his Deatly, than he had done in the time of all his Life. This <hi>Ship,</hi> for the ſpace of 15. hours, ſate like a Stagge amongſt Hounds, at the bay, and was ſeiged, and fought with, in turne, by 15. great Ships of <hi>Spaine;</hi> Part of a Nauy of 55. Ships in all; The reſt like Abettors looking on a farre off. And
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:433:31"/> amongſt the 15. Ships that fought, the great <hi>Sant Philippo</hi> was one; A Ship of 1500. tonne; Prince of the twelue <hi>Sea Apoſtles;</hi> Which was right glad, when ſhe was ſhifted off from the <hi>Reuenge.</hi> This braue ſhip the <hi>Reuenge,</hi> being manned on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with 200. (Souldiers and Mariners,) whereof 80. lay ſicke, yet neuertheleſſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Fight maintained (as was ſaid) of 15. houres, and two Ships of the Enemy ſunke by her ſide; Beſides many more torne and battered, and great ſlaughter of Men; neuer came to be entred, but was taken by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; The Enemies themſelues hauing in admiration the Vertue of the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and the whole Tragedy of that Ship.</p>
                  <p>In the yeare 1596, was the Second <hi>Inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> that we made vpon the Maine Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories of <hi>Spaine;</hi> Proſperouſly atchieued by that Worthy and Famous, <hi>Robert Earle of Eſſex,</hi> in conſort with the Noble <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> that now liueth, then <hi>Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</hi> This Iourny was like Lightning; For in the ſpace of 14. hours, the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spaines Nauy</hi> was deſtroyed, &amp; the Town of <hi>Cadez</hi>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:433:32"/> taken. The <hi>Nauy</hi> was no leſſe than 50. tall Ships, beſides 20. Gallies to attend them. The Ships were ſtraight waies beaten, &amp; put to flight, with ſuch terrour, as the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> in the end, were their owne Executioners, and fired them all with their owne Hands. The Gallies, by the benefit of the Shores and Shallowes, got away. The Towne was a faire, ſtrong, well built, and rich City; Famous in Antiquity, and now moſt ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of for this Diſaſter. It was manned with 4000. Souldiers Foot, and ſome 400. Horſe; It was ſacked, and burned, though great Clemency was vſed towards the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants. But that which is no leſſe ſtrange than the ſudden Victory, is the great patience of the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> Who, though wee ſtaid vpon the place diuers dayes, yet neuer offered vs any play then, nor euer put vs in ſuit, by any Action of Reuenge, or Reparation, at any time after.</p>
                  <p>In the yeare 1600. was the Battell of <hi>Newport</hi> in the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> where the Armies of the <hi>Arch-Duke,</hi> and the <hi>States,</hi> tried it out by a iuſt Battell. This was the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:433:32"/> only Battell, that was fought in thoſe Countries, theſe many yeares. For Battels in the <hi>French Warres</hi> haue beene frequent; But in the <hi>Warres</hi> of <hi>Flanders,</hi> rare, as the Nature of a Defenſiue requireth. The Forces of both Armies were not much vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equall: That of the <hi>States</hi> exceeded ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what in Number; But that againe was recompenſed in the Quality of the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; For thoſe of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Part were of the Flower of all their Forces. The <hi>Arch-Duke</hi> was the Aſſailant, and the Preuenter, and had the fruit of his Diligence and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerity. For he had charged certaine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of <hi>Scottiſhmen,</hi> to the Number of eight hundred, ſent to make good a Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and thereby ſeuered from the Body of the Army, and cut them all in peeces: For they like a braue Infantery, when they could make no honourable Retreit, and would take no diſhonourable Flight, made good the place with their Liues. This Entrance of the Battell did whet the Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> though it dulled their Swords; So as they came proudly
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:433:33"/> on, confident to defeat the whole Armie. The Encounter of the Maine Battell, which followed, was a iuſt Encounter, not haſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to a ſudden Rout, nor the Fortune of the day reſting vpon a few former Ranks, but foughten our to the proofe by ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Squadrons, and not without variety of ſucceſſe; <hi>Stat pedi pes, denſuſque viro vir.</hi> There fell out an Errour in the <hi>Dutch</hi> Army, by the ouerhaſty Medly of ſome of their Men, with the Enemies, which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the Playing of their great Ordnance. But the End was, that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were vtterly defeated, and neare 5000. of their Men, in the Fight, and in the Execution, ſlaine, and taken; Amongſt whom were many of the principall Perſons of their Army. The Honour of the Day was, both by the Enemy, and the <hi>Dutch</hi> themſelues, aſcribed vnto the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> Of whom Sir <hi>Francis Vere,</hi> in a priuate <hi>Commentary,</hi> which he wrote of that Seruice, leaueth teſtified; That of 1500. in number, (for they were no more,) 800. were ſlaine in the field; And (which is almoſt incredible in a day of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:433:33"/> victory,) of the remaining 700. two only Men came off vnhurt. Amongſt the reſt Sir <hi>Francis Vere</hi> himſelfe had the principall honour of the ſeruice, vnto whom the Prince of <hi>Aurange</hi> (as is ſaid) did tranſmit the Direction of the Army for that day. And in the next place, Sir <hi>Horace Vere</hi> his Brother, that now liueth, who was the principall in the Actiue part. The Seruice alſo, of Sir <hi>Edward Cecill,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Ogle,</hi> and diuers other braue Gentlemen, was emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent.</p>
                  <p>In the yeare 1601. followed the Battell of <hi>Kinſale,</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi> By this <hi>Spaniſh Inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> (which was in September that yeare,) a Man may gheſſe, how long time a <hi>Spaniard</hi> will liue in <hi>Iriſh</hi> Ground; which is a matter of a Quarter of a yeare, or foure Moneths at the moſt. For they had all the Aduantages in the world; And no Man would haue thought, (conſidering the ſmall Forces imployed againſt them,) that they could haue beene driuen out ſo ſoone. They obtained, without reſiſtance, in the end of September, the Towne of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:433:34"/> 
                     <hi>Kinſale;</hi> A ſmall Garriſon of 150. <hi>Engliſh,</hi> leauing the Towne vpon the <hi>Spaniards</hi> approach, and the Towneſmen receiuing the <hi>Forrainers</hi> as Friends. The Number of <hi>Spaniards,</hi> that put themſelues into <hi>Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſale,</hi> was 2000. Men, Souldiers of old Bands, vnder the command of <hi>Don Ihuan d' Aquila,</hi> a Man of good valour. The <hi>Towne</hi> was ſtrong of it ſelfe; Neither wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted there any Induſtry to fortifie it on all parts, and make it tenable, according to the Skill and Diſcipline of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. At that time the <hi>Rebels</hi> were proud, being encouraged vpon former Succeſſes; For though the then Deputy, the Lord <hi>Mountioy,</hi> and Sir <hi>George Carew,</hi> Preſident of <hi>Munſter,</hi> had performed diuers good Serui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to their preiudice; Yet the Defeat they had giuen the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> at <hi>Blacke-water,</hi> not long before; And the Treaty (too much to their honour,) with the <hi>Earle of Eſſex,</hi> was yet freſh in their memory. The <hi>Deputy</hi> loſt no time, but made haſte to haue reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered the Towne, before new Succours came, and ſate downe before it in Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:433:34"/> and laid ſiege to it by the ſpace of three Winter Moneths, or more: During which time, Sallies were made by the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> but they were beaten in with loſſe. In Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary came freſh Succours from <hi>Spaine,</hi> to the number of 2000. more, vnder the Conduct of <hi>Alonzo D' Ocampo.</hi> Vpon the Comforts of theſe Succours, <hi>Tirone</hi> and <hi>Odonnell,</hi> drew vp their Forces together, to the number of 7000. beſides the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Regiments, and tooke the field, reſolued to reſcue the Towne, and to giue the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> battell. So here was the Caſe: An Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of <hi>Engliſh,</hi> of ſome 6000, waſted and tired with along Winters Siege; Engaged in the middeſt, betweene an Armie of a greater Number than themſelues, freſh and in vigour, on the one ſide; And a Towne ſtrong in Fortification, and ſtrong in Men, on the other. But what was the Euent? This in few words; That after the <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Forces had come on, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelues in ſome Brauery, they were content to giue the <hi>Engliſh</hi> the honour, as to charge them firſt; And when it came
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:433:35"/> to the Charge, there appeared no other dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene the Valour of the <hi>Iriſh Rebels,</hi> and the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> but that the one ranne away before they were char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and the other ſtraight after. And againe, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> that were in the towne, had ſo good Memories of their loſſes, in their former Sallies, as the Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of an Army, which came for their deliuerance, could not draw them forth againe. To conclude, there ſucceeded an abſolute victory for the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> with the ſlaughter of aboue two thouſand of the Enemie; The taking of nine Enſignes, whereof ſix <hi>Spaniſh;</hi> The taking of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Generall, <hi>D' Ocampo,</hi> Priſoner; And this with the loſſe of ſo few of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as is ſcarce credible; Being (as hath beene rather confidently, than credibly reported,) but of one Man, the Cornet of Sir <hi>Richard Greame;</hi> though not a few hurt. There followed immediately after the Defeat, a preſent yeelding vp of the Towne by Compoſition; And not only ſo, but an Auoiding (by expreſſe Articles of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:433:35"/> Treaty accorded) of all other <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Forces thorowout all <hi>Ireland,</hi> from the Places and Neſts where they had ſetl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d themſelues, in greater ſtrength, (as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the naturall Situation of the Places,) than that was of <hi>Kinſale:</hi> Which were, <hi>Caſtle-hauen, Baltimore,</hi> and <hi>Beere-hauen.</hi> Indeed they went away with ſound of Trumpet; For they did nothing but publiſh and trumpet all the Reproaches they could deuiſe, againſt the <hi>Iriſh Land,</hi> and Nation; Inſomuch as <hi>D' Aquila</hi> ſaid in open Treaty; <hi>That when the Deuill, vpon the Mount, did ſhew Chriſt all the Kingdomes of the Earth, and the Glory of them, hee did not doubt, but the Deuill left out Ireland, and kept it for himſelfe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ceaſe here, omitting not a few other Proofes of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Valour and Fortune, in theſe later times: As at the Suburbs of <hi>Paris,</hi> at the <hi>Raueline,</hi> at <hi>Druſe</hi> in <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy,</hi> ſome Encounters in <hi>Britanny,</hi> and at <hi>Oſtend,</hi> and diuers others; Partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome of them haue not beene pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Encounters between the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:433:36"/> the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> And partly becauſe Others of them haue not beene of that greatneſſe, as to haue ſorted in company with the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars formerly recited. It is true, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all the late Aduentures, the Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of Sir <hi>Francis Drake,</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn Haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins,</hi> into the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> was vnfortunate; Yet in ſuch ſort, as it doth not breake or interrupt our Preſcription; To haue had the better of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> vpon all fights of late. For the Diſaſter of that Iourney was cauſed chiefly by ſickneſſe; As might well appeare by the Deaths of both the Generals, (Sir <hi>Francis Drake,</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn Hawkins,</hi>) of the ſame ſickneſſe amongſt the reſt. The Land Enterpriſe of <hi>Panama,</hi> was an ill meaſured and imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Counſell, For it was grounded vpon a falſe account, that the Paſſages to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Panama</hi> were no better fortified, than <hi>Drake</hi> had left them. But yet, it ſorted not to any Fight of importance, but to a Retreit, after the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had proued the ſtrength of their firſt Fort, and had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the two other Forts beyond, by
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:433:36"/> which they were to haue marched. It is true, that in the Returne of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleet, they were ſet vpon by <hi>Auellaneda,</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall of 20. great ſhips <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> our Fleet being but 14, full of ſicke men, depriued of their two Generalls by Sea, and hauing no pretence but to iourny homewards: And yet the <hi>Spaniards</hi> did but ſalute them about the <hi>Cape</hi> de <hi>los Corientes,</hi> with ſome ſmall offer of Fight, and came off with loſſe; Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it was ſuch a new thing for the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> to receiue ſo little hurt, vpon dealing with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as <hi>Auellaneda</hi> made great bragges of it, for no greater matter, than the waiting vpon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> afarre off, from <hi>Cape</hi> de <hi>los Corientes</hi> to <hi>Cape Antonio;</hi> Which neuertheleſſe, in the Language of a Souldier, and of a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> hee called a <hi>Chace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But before I proceed further, it is good to meet with an Obiection, which if it bee not remoued, the Concluſion of <hi>Experience,</hi> from the time paſt, to the time preſent, will not bee ſound and perfect. For it will be ſaid, that in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:433:37"/> times, (whereof wee haue ſpoken,) <hi>Spaine</hi> was not ſo mighty as now it is; And <hi>England</hi> on the other ſide, was more afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand in all matters of Power. Therefore, let vs compare with indifferency, theſe Diſparities of times, and we ſhall plainly perceiue, that they make for the aduantage of <hi>England,</hi> at this preſent time. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we will leſſe wander in Generalities, we wil ſix the Compariſon to preciſe Times; Comparing the State of <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>England</hi> in the yeare 88. with this preſent yeare that now runneth. In handling this Point, I will not meddle with any Perſonall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſons, of the <hi>Princes, Counſellors,</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders</hi> by Sea or Land, that were then, and that are now, in both Kingdomes, <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>England;</hi> But only reſt vpon Reall Points, for the true Ballancing of the <hi>State,</hi> of the <hi>Forces,</hi> and <hi>Affaires</hi> of both Times. And yet theſe Perſonall Compariſons I omit not, but that I could euidently ſhew, that euen in theſe Perſonall Reſpects, the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance ſwayes on our part: But becauſe I would ſay nothing, that may ſauour of a
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:433:37"/> ſpirit of Flattery, or Cenſure, of the preſen Gouernment.</p>
                  <p>Firſt therefore, it is certaine, that <hi>Spaine</hi> hath not now a foot of Ground, in quiet poſſeſſion, more than it had in 88. As for the <hi>Valtoline,</hi> and the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> it is a Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ime in State, that all Countries of new Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, till they be ſetled, are rather Matters of Burthen, than of Strength. On the other ſide, <hi>England</hi> hath <hi>Scotland</hi> vnited, and <hi>Ireland</hi> reduced to obedience, and plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which are mighty Augmentations.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, in 88, the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> able alone to counterpoize <hi>Spaine</hi> it ſelfe, (much more in coniunction,) was torne with the Party of the League, which gaue law to their King, and depended wholly vpon <hi>Spaine.</hi> Now <hi>France</hi> is vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnder a valiant young King, generally obeyed if he will himſelfe; King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre</hi> as well as of <hi>France;</hi> And that is no wayes taken Priſoner, though he be tied in a double chaine of Alliance, with <hi>Spaine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, in 88, there ſate in the <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> a fierce Thundring Frier, that would
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:433:38"/> ſet all at ſix and ſeuen; Or at ſix and fiue, if you allude to his Name. And though hee would after haue turned his teeth vpon <hi>Spaine,</hi> yet he was taken order with, before it came to that. Now there is aſcended to the Papacy, a Perſonage, that came in by a chaſte Election, no wayes obliged to the Party of the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> A man bred in Ambaſſages &amp; Affaires of State, That hath much of the Prince, and nothing of the Frier; And one, that though he loue the Chaire of the Papacy well, yet hee loueth the Carpet aboue the Chaire; That is, <hi>Italy,</hi> and the Liberties thereof, well likewiſe.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, in 88, the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> was a ſtranger to <hi>England,</hi> and rather incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to <hi>Spaine;</hi> Now the King is incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Bloud of <hi>England,</hi> and Engaged in the Quarrell of the <hi>Palatinate.</hi> Then alſo <hi>Venice, Sauoy,</hi> and the <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Cities</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> had but a dull Feare of the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Spaine,</hi> vpon a generall Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion only, of the ſpreading and ambitious Deſignes of that <hi>Nation:</hi> Now that Feare is ſharpened and pointed, by the <hi>Spaniard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:433:38"/> late Enterpriſes, vpon the <hi>Valtoline</hi> and the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> which come nearer them.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly and laſtly, the <hi>Dutch</hi> (which is the <hi>Spaniards</hi> perpetuall Duelliſt,) hath now, at this preſent, fiue Ships to one, and the like Proportion in Treaſure and Wealth, to that they had in 88. Neither is it poſſible, (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out,) that the Cofers of <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould now bee fuller, than they were in 88. For at that Time <hi>Spaine</hi> had no other Warres ſaue thoſe of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> which were growne into an Ordinary: Now they haue had coupled therewith, the Extraordinary of the <hi>Valtoline,</hi> and the <hi>Palatinate.</hi> And ſo I conclude my Anſwer to the Obiection raiſed, touching the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of times; Not entring into more ſecret Paſſages of State; But keeping that Character of Stile, whereof <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; <hi>Plus ſignificat quàm loquitur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here I would paſſe ouer from Matter of <hi>Experience,</hi> were it not that I held it neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, to diſcouer a wonderfull Erroneous obſeruation that walketh about, and is commonly receiued, contrary to all the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:433:39"/> true Account of Time, and Experience. It is, that the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> where he once get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in, will ſeldome (or neuer) be got out againe. But nothing is leſſe true than this. Not long ſince they got footing at <hi>Breſt,</hi> and ſome other parts in <hi>French Brittaine,</hi> &amp; after quitted them. They had <hi>Calais, Ardes,</hi> and <hi>Amiens,</hi> and rendred them, or were beaten out. They had ſince <hi>Verſeilles,</hi> and faire left it. They had the other day the <hi>Valtoline,</hi> and now haue put it in depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite. What they will doe with <hi>Ormus,</hi> which the <hi>Perſian</hi> hath taken from them, we ſhall ſee. So that to ſpeake truly of later Times, they haue rather poched and offered at a Number of Enterpriſes, than maintained any conſtantly, quite contrary to that idle Tradition. In more ancient times, (lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing their Purchaſes in <hi>Affricke,</hi> which they after abandoned,) when their great <hi>Emperour Charles</hi> had claſped <hi>Germany,</hi> (almoſt) in his fiſt, he was forced, in the end, to goe from <hi>Isburg,</hi> (and as if it had beene in a Maſque, by Torch-light,) and to quit euery foot in <hi>Germany</hi> round
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:433:39"/> that he had gotten; Which I doubt not, will be the hereditary Iſſue of this late Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of the <hi>Palatinate.</hi> And ſo I conclude the Ground, that I haue to think, that <hi>Spain</hi> will be no Ouermatch to <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> if his <hi>Maieſty</hi> ſhall enter into a Warre, out of <hi>Experience,</hi> and the Records of Time.</p>
                  <p>For Grounds of <hi>Reaſon</hi> they are many: I will extract the principall, and open them briefly, and (as it were) in the Bud. For <hi>Situ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,</hi> I paſſe it ouer; Though it be no ſmall point: <hi>England, Scotland, Ireland,</hi> and our good Confederates the <hi>Vnited Prouinces,</hi> lie al in a plump together, not acceſſible but by Sea, or at leaſt by paſſing of great Riuers, which are Naturall Fortifications. As for the Dominions of <hi>Spaine,</hi> they are ſo ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, as it yeeldeth great choice of the ſcenes of the Warre, and promiſeth ſlow Succours vnto ſuch Part, as ſhall bee at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted. There be three maine parts of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Puiſſance; Men, Mony,</hi> and <hi>Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates</hi> For <hi>Men,</hi> there are to be conſidered, <hi>Valour,</hi> and <hi>Number.</hi> Of <hi>Valour</hi> I ſpeake
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:433:40"/> not: Take it from the Witneſſes that haue beene produced before: Yet the old obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation is not vntrue; That the <hi>Spaniards Valour</hi> lieth in the Eye of the Looker on; But the <hi>Engliſh Valour</hi> lieth about the Souldiers Heart. A <hi>Valour</hi> of Glory, and a <hi>Valour</hi> of Naturall Courage, are two things. But let that paſſe, and let vs ſpeake of <hi>Number. Spaine</hi> is a Nation thin ſowne of People; Partly by reaſon of the Sterility of the Soile; And partly becauſe their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues are exhauſted by ſo many Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in ſuch vaſt Territories as they poſſeſſe. So that it hath beene counted a kind of Miracle, to ſee ten or twelue thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Natiue <hi>Spaniards</hi> in an Army. And it is certaine, (as we haue touched it a little before in paſſage,) that the Secret of the Power of <hi>Spaine,</hi> conſiſteth in a Veterane Army, compounded of Miſcellany Forces of all Nations, which for many yeares they haue had on foot vpon one occaſion or other: And if there ſhould happen the Misfortune of a Battell, it would be a long worke to draw on ſupplies. They tell a
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:433:40"/> Tale, of a <hi>Spaniſh Ambaſſadour,</hi> that was brought to ſee the Treaſury of <hi>S. Marke</hi> at <hi>Venice,</hi> and ſtill he looked downe to the Ground; And being asked, why he ſo looked downe, ſaid; <hi>He was looking to ſee whether their Treaſure had any Root, (ſo that if it were ſpent, it would grow againe,) as his Maſters had.</hi> But howſoeuer it be of their Treaſure, certainly their Forces haue ſcarce any Root; Or at leaſt ſuch a Root, as buddeth forth poorely, and ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. It is true, they haue the <hi>Wallons,</hi> who are tall Souldiers; But that is but a Spot of Ground. But, on the other ſide, there is not in the world againe, ſuch a Spring and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary of braue Militar People, as is <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland, Ireland,</hi> and the <hi>Vnited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces.</hi> So as if <hi>Warres</hi> ſhould mowe them downe neuer ſo faſt, yet they may be ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly ſupplyed, and come vp againe.</p>
                  <p>For <hi>Money,</hi> no doubt it is the principall Part of the Greatneſſe of <hi>Spaine;</hi> For by that they maintaine their Veteran Army; And <hi>Spaine</hi> is the only State of <hi>Europe,</hi> that is a <hi>Money grower.</hi> But in this Part,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:433:41"/> of all others, is moſt to be conſidered, the tickliſh and brittle State of the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Spaine.</hi> Their <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> conſiſteth in their <hi>Treaſure;</hi> Their <hi>Treaſure</hi> in their <hi>Indies;</hi> And their <hi>Indies,</hi> (if it bee well weighed,) are indeed but an Acceſſion to ſuch, as are Maſters by Sea. So as this Ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltree, whereupon their Greatneſſe tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, is ſoone cut in two, by any that ſhall be ſtronger than they by Sea. Herein therefore I refer me to the Opinions of all Men, (Enemies, or whomſoeuer,) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that the Maritime Forces of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> and the <hi>Vnited Prouinces,</hi> bee not able to beat the <hi>Spaniard</hi> at Sea. For if that bee ſo, the Linkes of that chaine, whereby they hold their Greatneſſe, are diſſolued. Now if it be ſaid, that admit the Caſe of <hi>Spaine</hi> bee ſuch, as wee haue made it, yet wee ought to deſcend into our owne Caſe, which wee ſhall finde (perhaps) not to be in State, (for Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,) to enter into a Warre with <hi>Spaine.</hi> To which I anſwer; I know no ſuch thing; The Mint beateth well; And the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:433:41"/> Pulſes of the Peoples Hearts beat well. But there is another Point that taketh away quite this Obiection: For whereas <hi>Warres</hi> are generally Cauſes of <hi>Pouerty,</hi> or Conſumption; on the contrary part, the ſpeciall Nature of this <hi>Warre</hi> with <hi>Spaine,</hi> (if it be made by Sea,) is like to be a Lucra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue and Reſtoratiue <hi>Warre.</hi> So that, if we goe roundly on at the firſt, the <hi>Warre</hi> in continuance will finde it ſelfe. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you muſt make a great difference, betweene <hi>Hercules</hi> Labours by Land, and <hi>Iaſons</hi> Voyage by Sea for the Golden Fleece.</p>
                  <p>For <hi>Confederates,</hi> I will not take vpon mee the knowledge, how the Princes, States, and Counſels of <hi>Europe,</hi> at this day, ſtand affected towards <hi>Spaine;</hi> For that trencheth into the ſecret Occurrents of the preſent Time, wherewith in all this Treatiſe I haue forborne to meddle. But to ſpeake of that which lieth open and in view: I ſee much Matter of Quarrell and Iealouſie, but little of Amity and Truſt towards <hi>Spaine,</hi> almoſt in all other Eſtates.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:433:42"/> I ſee <hi>France</hi> is in competition with them, for three noble Portions of their Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie; <hi>Nauarre, Naples,</hi> and <hi>Millaine;</hi> And now freſhly in difference with them about the <hi>Valtoline.</hi> I ſee once in thirty or forty yeares commeth a <hi>Pope,</hi> that caſteth his eye vpon the Kingdome of <hi>Naples,</hi> to recouer it to the Church: As it was in the mindes of <hi>Iulius</hi> 2. <hi>Paulus</hi> 4. and <hi>Ziſtus</hi> 5. As for that great Body of <hi>Germanie;</hi> I ſee they haue greater reaſon to <hi>confederate</hi> themſelues with the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> or <hi>Denmarke,</hi> for the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of the <hi>Germaine Nation,</hi> and for the Expulſion of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and forraine For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, than they had in the yeares 1552. and 1553. At which time, they contracted a League with <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, the <hi>French</hi> King, vpon the ſame Articles, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, who had impatro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized himſelfe of a great Part of <hi>Germany,</hi> through diſcord of the <hi>German Princes,</hi> which himſelfe had ſowen and fomented; Which League at that time did the Deed, and draue out all the <hi>Spaniards</hi> out of that
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:433:42"/> part of <hi>Germany;</hi> And re-integrated that Nation in their ancient Liberty and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. For the <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> though <hi>Spaine</hi> hath had yet not much actuall diſturbance there, except it haue beene from <hi>England;</hi> Yet neuertheleſſe I ſee all Princes lay a kind of claime vnto them; Accounting the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>Spaine,</hi> but as a Monopolie of thoſe large Countries, wherein they haue, in great part, but an Imaginary Poſſeſſion. For <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frick</hi> vpon the <hi>Weſt,</hi> the Moores of <hi>Valentia</hi> expulſed, and their Allies, doe yet hang as a Cloud or Storme ouer <hi>Spaine. Gabor</hi> on the Eaſt, is like an Anniuerſary Wind, that riſeth euery yeare once vpon the Party of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria.</hi> And <hi>Perſia</hi> hath entred into Hoſtility with <hi>Spaine,</hi> and giuen them the firſt blow by taking of <hi>Ormus.</hi> It is within euery mans Obſeruation alſo, that <hi>Venice</hi> doth thinke their State almoſt on fire, if the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> hold the <hi>Valtoline.</hi> That <hi>Sauoy</hi> hath learned by freſh experience; That Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with <hi>Spaine</hi> is no Security againſt the Ambition of <hi>Spaine;</hi> And that of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaria</hi> hath likewiſe beene taught, that Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:433:43"/> and Seruice doth oblige the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard</hi> but from day to day. Neither doe I ſay, for all this, but that <hi>Spaine</hi> may rectifie much of this ill Bloud, by their particular and cunning Negotiations: But yet there it is in the Body, and may breake out, no man knoweth when, into ill Accidents: But at leaſt it ſheweth plainly that which ſerueth for our purpoſe; That <hi>Spain</hi> is much deſtitute of Aſſured and Confident <hi>Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates.</hi> And therefore I will conclude this Part, with the Speech of a Counſellour of State, in <hi>Spaine,</hi> at this day, which was not without Salt. He ſaid to his Maſter, the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> that now is, vpon occaſion: <hi>Sir, I will tell your Maieſty thus much for your comfort; Your Maieſty hath but two Enemies; Whereof the one is, all the World; And the other is, your owne Miniſters.</hi> And thus I end the Second Maine Part, I propounded to ſpeake of; which was, The <hi>Ballancing</hi> of the <hi>Forces,</hi> betweene the <hi>Kings Maieſtie,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> if a Warre muſt follow.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:433:43"/>
                  <p>AN ADVERTISEMENT TOVCHING AN Holy Warre.</p>
                  <p>Written in the yeare 1622.</p>
                  <p>Whereunto the Author prefixed an Epiſtle to the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> laſt deceaſed.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device of John Haviland</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>LONDON, ¶ Printed by IOHN HAVILAND for <hi>Humphrey Robinſon.</hi> 1629.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:433:44"/>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:433:44"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER in God, LANCELLOT ANDREWES, Lord Biſhop of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi> and Counſellour of Eſtate to his MAIESTIE.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongst Conſolations, it is not the leaſt, to repreſent to a Mans ſelfe, like <hi>Examples</hi> of Calamitie in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. For <hi>Examples</hi> giue a quicker Jmpreſsion, than <hi>Arguments;</hi> And
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:433:45"/> beſides they certifie vs that, which the <hi>Scripture</hi> alſo tendreth for ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; <hi>That no new Thing is happened vnto vs.</hi> This they doe the better, by how much the <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> are liker in circumſtances, to our owne Caſe; And more eſpecially, if they fall vpon <hi>Perſons,</hi> that are greater, and worthier, than our ſelues. For as it ſauoureth of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>anity, to match our ſelues highly, in our owne conceit; So on the otherſide, it is a good ſound Concluſion, that if our Betters haue ſuſtained the like Euents, wee haue the leſſe cauſe to be grieued.</p>
                  <p>Jn this kinde of Conſolation, I haue not beene wanting to my Selfe; Though as a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> I haue taſted (through <hi>Gods</hi> great goodneſſe,) of higher Remedies. Hauing therefore,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:433:45"/> through the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>arietie of my Reading, ſet before me, many <hi>Examples,</hi> both of Ancient and Later Times, my Thoughts (I confeſſe) haue chiefly ſtayed vpon three <hi>Particulars,</hi> as the moſt Eminent, and the moſt Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling. All three <hi>Perſons,</hi> that had held chiefe place of Authority in their Countries; All three ruined, not by Warre, or by any other Diſaſter, but by Juſtice, and Sentence, as Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, and Criminalls; All three famous Writers, inſomuch as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of their Calamity, is now as to Poſterity, but as a little Picture of Night-worke, remaining a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the faire, and excellent Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, of their Acts, and Works. And all three (if that were any thing to the matter,) fit <hi>Examples</hi> to quench
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:433:46"/> any Mans Ambition of Riſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; For that they were euery one of them reſtored with great glory, but to their further Ruine and Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, ending in a violent Death. The <hi>Men</hi> were, <hi>Demoſthenes, Cicero,</hi> and <hi>Seneca;</hi> Perſons, that J durſt not claime Affinity with, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Similitude of our Fortunes had contracted it. When I had caſt mine Eyes vpon theſe <hi>Examples,</hi> J was carried on further to obſerue, how they did beare their Fortunes, and principally, how they did employ their Times, being baniſhed, and diſabled for Publike Buſineſſe; To the end, that J might learne by them; And that they might be, as well my Counſellours, as my Comforters. Wherupon I happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to note, how diuerſly, their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:433:46"/> wrought vpon them, eſpecially in that point, at which I did moſt aime, which was the employing of their Times, and Pens. Jn <hi>Cicero,</hi> I ſaw, that during his Baniſhment, (which was almoſt two yeares,) he was ſo ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and deiected, as he wrote nothing, but a few Womaniſh <hi>Epiſtles.</hi> And yet, in mine opinion, he had leaſt reaſon of the Three, to be diſcouraged: For that although it was iudged, and iudged by the higheſt kinde of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in forme of a <hi>Statute,</hi> or <hi>Law,</hi> that he ſhould be baniſhed; And his whole Eſtate confiſcated, and ſeized; And his houſes pulled downe; And that it ſhould be highly penall, for any Man, to propound his Repeale; Yet his Caſe, euen then, had no great Blot of Ignominy, but it was thought,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:433:47"/> but a Tempeſt of Popularitie, which ouerthrew him. <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, though his Caſe was foule, being condemned for <hi>Bribery;</hi> And not ſimple <hi>Bribery,</hi> but <hi>Bribery</hi> in the Nature of Treaſon, and Diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty; yet neuertheleſſe tooke ſo little knowledge of his Fortune, as during his Baniſhment, hee did much buſie himſelfe, and entermeddle with mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>State;</hi> And tooke vpon him to Counſell the <hi>State,</hi> (as if he had beene ſtill at the Helme,) by letters; As ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by ſome <hi>Epiſtles</hi> of his, which are extant. <hi>Seneca</hi> indeed, who was condemned, for many <hi>Corruptions,</hi> and <hi>Crimes,</hi> and baniſhed into a ſolitary <hi>Iſland,</hi> kept a Meane; And though his penne did not freeſe, yet he abſtained from intruding into Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:433:47"/> of Buſineſſe; But ſpent his time, in writing <hi>Books,</hi> of excellent Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Vſe, for all Ages; Though he might haue made better Choyce, (ſometimes) of his <hi>Dedications.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe <hi>Examples</hi> confirmed mee much in a Reſolution, (whereunto J was otherwiſe inclined,) to ſpend my Time wholly in Writing; And to put forth that poore <hi>Talent,</hi> or halfe <hi>Talent,</hi> or what it is, that God hath giuen me, not as heretofore to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>Exchanges,</hi> but to <hi>Banks,</hi> or <hi>Mounts</hi> of Perpetuity, which will not breake. Therefore hauing not long ſince, ſet forth a part of my <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration;</hi> Which is the Worke, that in mine owne iudgement, <hi>(Si nunquam fallit Imago,)</hi> J doe moſt eſteeme; I thinke to proceed in ſome
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:433:48"/> new parts thereof. And although J haue receiued from many Parts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, Teſtimonies touching that Worke, ſuch as beyond which J could not expect at the firſt, in ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſe an Argument; yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe J haue iuſt cauſe to doubt, that it flies too high ouer Mens Heads: I haue a purpoſe therefore, (though I breake the order of Time,) to draw it downe to the ſenſe, by ſome Patternes of a <hi>Naturall Story,</hi> and <hi>Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And againe, for that my <hi>Booke</hi> of <hi>Aduancement of Learning,</hi> may be ſome Preparatiue, or Key, for the better opening of the <hi>Inſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration;</hi> Becauſe it exhibit's a Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, of new Conceits, and old; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the <hi>Inſtauration,</hi> giues the new vnmixed, otherwiſe than with ſome
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:433:48"/> little Aſperſion of the old, for taſtes ſake; J haue thought good to procure a <hi>Tranſlation</hi> of that <hi>Booke,</hi> into the <hi>Generall Language,</hi> not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great and ample Additions, and Enrichment thereof; Eſpecially in the <hi>Second Booke,</hi> which handleth the <hi>Partition</hi> of <hi>Sciences:</hi> In ſuch ſort, as I hold it may ſerue, in lieu of the <hi>Firſt Part,</hi> of the <hi>Inſtauration,</hi> and acquit my promiſe in that part. Againe, becauſe I cannot altogether deſert, the Ciuill Perſon, that I haue borne; Which if I ſhould forget, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough would remember; J haue alſo entred into a worke touching <hi>Lawes;</hi> Propounding a Character of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> in a middle terme, betweene the Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culatiue, and Reuerend diſcourſes of Philoſophers, and the Writings of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:433:49"/> 
                     <hi>Lawyers,</hi> which are tied, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to their particular <hi>Lawes.</hi> And although it be true, that J had a purpoſe, to make a particular <hi>Digeſt,</hi> or Recompilement, of the <hi>Lawes,</hi> of mine owne Nation; Yet becauſe it is a Worke of Aſsiſtance, and that, that I cannot maſter by mine owne Forces, and Penne, J haue laid it aſide. Now hauing in the <hi>Worke</hi> of my <hi>Inſtauration,</hi> had in contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, the generall Good of <hi>Men,</hi> in their very Being, and the Dowries of Nature; And in my <hi>Worke</hi> of <hi>Lawes,</hi> the generall good of <hi>Men</hi> likewiſe, in Society, and the Dowries of Gouernment; I thought in duty I owed ſomewhat vnto mine owne <hi>Country,</hi> which J euer loued; Jnſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as although my Place, hath
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:433:49"/> beene farre aboue my deſert, yet my Thoughts, and Cares concerning the Good thereof, were beyond, and ouer, and aboue my place: So now being (as I am) no more able to doe my <hi>Countrey</hi> Seruice, it remained vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, to doe it Honour: Which J haue endeuoured to doe, in my <hi>VVorke,</hi> of the <hi>Raigne,</hi> of <hi>King HENRY</hi> the <hi>Seuenth.</hi> As for my <hi>Eſſayes,</hi> and ſome other Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of that nature, I count them, but as the Recreations of my other Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and in that ſort purpoſe to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue them; Though J am not ignorant, that thoſe kind of <hi>VVritings,</hi> would, with leſſe paines, and embracement, (perhaps,) yeeld more Luſtre, and Reputation to my Name, than thoſe other, which I haue in hand. But J
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:433:50"/> account the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, that a Man ſhould ſeeke, of the publiſhing of his owne <hi>VVritings</hi> before his Death, to be but an vntimely Anticipation of that, which is proper to follow a Man, and not to goe along with him.</p>
                  <p>But reuoluing with my ſelfe, my <hi>Writings,</hi> as well thoſe which I haue publiſhed, as thoſe, which I had in hand, me thought they went all into the <hi>City,</hi> and none into the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;</hi> Where becauſe I haue found, ſo great Conſolation, J deſire likewiſe to make ſome poore Oblation. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore J haue choſen an Argument, mixt of <hi>Religious</hi> and <hi>Ciuill</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations; And likewiſe mixt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Contemplatiue,</hi> and <hi>Actiue.</hi> For who can tell, whether there may not be an <hi>Exoriere aliquis?</hi> Great
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:433:50"/> Matters (eſpecially if they be <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious</hi>) haue (many times) ſmall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings; And the Platforme, may draw on the Building. This <hi>Worke,</hi> becauſe I was euer an Enemy to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring <hi>Dedications,</hi> I haue dedicated to your Lordſhip; Jn reſpect of our ancient, and priuate Acquaintance; And becauſe amongst the Men of our Times, I hold you in eſpeciall Reuerence.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Lordſhips louing Friend Fr. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. ALBAN.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:433:51"/>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:433:51"/>
                  <head>AN ADVERTISEMENT TOVCHING AN HOLY WARRE.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>The Perſons that ſpeake.</hi> EVSEBIVS. GAMALIEL. ZEBEDAEVS. MARTIVS. EVPOLIS. POLLIO.</stage>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here met at</hi> Paris,<note place="margin">Characters <hi>of the</hi> Perſons. <hi>E ſebius</hi> bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Diuine. <hi>Gamaliel</hi> of a Proteſtant Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant. <hi>Zebedaeus</hi> of a Romiſh Catholike Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant. <hi>Martius</hi> of a Militar Man. <hi>Eupolis</hi> of a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique. <hi>Pollio</hi> of a Courtier.</note> (<hi>in the houſe of</hi> Eupolis,) Euſebius, Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedaeus, Gamaliel, Martius; <hi>All Perſons of eminent Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, but of ſeuerall Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> Eupolis <hi>himſelfe was alſo preſent: And while they were ſet in conference,</hi> Pollio <hi>came in to them from Court; And as ſoone as he ſaw them, after his witty and pleaſant manner, he ſaid.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:433:52"/> ſaid.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>POLLIO.</speaker>
                     <p>Here be Foure of you, I thinke, were able to make a good <hi>World;</hi> For you are as differing as the Foure <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and yet you are Friends. As for <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis,</hi> becauſe he is Temperate, and without Paſſion, hee may bee the <hi>Fifth Eſſence.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EVPOLIS.</speaker>
                     <p>If we fiue <hi>(Pollio,)</hi> make the <hi>Great World,</hi> you alone may make the <hi>Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle;</hi> Becauſe you profeſſe and practiſe both, to referre all Things to your Selfe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>POLLIO.</speaker>
                     <p>And what doe they that pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe it, and profeſſe it not?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EVPOLIS.</speaker>
                     <p>They are the leſſe Hardy, and the more Dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. But come, and fit downe with vs, for we were ſpeaking of the <hi>Affaires</hi> of <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> at this day: Wherein we would be glad alſo, to haue your Opinion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>POLLIO.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lords, I haue iourneyed this Morning, and it is now the Heat of the Day; Therefore your Lordſhips Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, had need content my Eares very well, to make them entreat mine Eyes to keepe open. But yet if you will giue mee leaue to awake you, when I thinke your Diſcourſes doe but ſleepe, I will keepe
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:433:52"/> watch the beſt I can.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EVPOLIS.</speaker>
                     <p>You can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe vs a greater Fauour. Onely I feare, you will thinke all our Diſcourſes, to be but the better ſort of Dreames: For good wiſhes, without power to effect, are not much more. But Sir, when you came in, <hi>Martius</hi> had both raiſed our Attentions, and affected vs with ſome Speech he had begunne; And it falleth out well, to ſhake off your Drowſineſſe, for it ſeemed to be the <hi>Trumpet</hi> of a <hi>Warre.</hi> And therefore, <hi>(Martius,)</hi> if it pleaſe you, to begin againe; For the Speech was ſuch, as deſerueth to be heard twice; And I aſſure you, your Audito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is not a little amended, by the preſence of <hi>Pollio.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MARTIVS.</speaker>
                     <p>When you came in, <hi>(Pollio,)</hi> I was ſaying freely to theſe Lords, that I had obſerued, how by the ſpace now, of halfe a <hi>Century</hi> of yeares, there had beene (if I may ſpeak it,) a Kind of Meanneſſe, in the Deſignes, &amp; Enterpriſes of <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> Warres with <hi>Subiects;</hi> Like an angry Sute for a Mans Owne, that mought be better ended by Accord. Some petty Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts of a Towne, or a Spot of Territory;
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:433:53"/> Like a Farmers Purchaſe of a Cloſe, or Nooke of Ground, that lay fit for him. And although the <hi>Warres</hi> had beene, for a <hi>Naples,</hi> or a <hi>Millaine,</hi> or a <hi>Portugall,</hi> or a <hi>Bohemia,</hi> yet theſe <hi>Warres</hi> were but as the <hi>Warres</hi> of Heathen, (Of <hi>Athens,</hi> or <hi>Sparta,</hi> or <hi>Rome,</hi>) for Secular Intereſt, or Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not worthy the <hi>Warfare</hi> of <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> (indeed) maketh her Miſſions, into the Extreme Parts, of the <hi>Nations,</hi> and <hi>Iſles;</hi> And it is well: But this is, <hi>Ecce Vnus Gladius hic.</hi> The <hi>Chriſtian Princes,</hi> and <hi>Potentates</hi> are they, that are wanting, to the Propagation of the <hi>Faith,</hi> by their <hi>Armes.</hi> Yet our <hi>Lord,</hi> that ſaid on Eatrh, to the <hi>Diſciples, Ite &amp; praedicate;</hi> Said from Heauen, to <hi>Conſtantine, In hoc ſigno Vince.</hi> What <hi>Chriſtian Souldier</hi> is there, that will not be touched, with a Religious Emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to ſee an <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> or of Saint <hi>Francis,</hi> or of Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> doe ſuch ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, for enlarging the <hi>Chriſtian Borders;</hi> And an <hi>Order</hi> of Saint <hi>Iago,</hi> or Saint <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael,</hi> or Saint <hi>George,</hi> only to Roab, and Feaſt, and performe Rites, and Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uances?
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:433:53"/> Surely the <hi>Merchants</hi> themſelues, ſhall riſe in iudgement againſt the <hi>Princes,</hi> and <hi>Nobles</hi> of <hi>Europe:</hi> For they haue made a great Path, in the Seas, vnto the Ends of the World; And ſet forth Ships, and Forces, of <hi>Spaniſh, Engliſh,</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> enough to make <hi>China</hi> tremble; And all this, for <hi>Pearle,</hi> or <hi>Stone,</hi> or <hi>Spices:</hi> But for the <hi>Pearle</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Heauen,</hi> Or the <hi>Stones</hi> of the <hi>Heauenly Hieruſalem,</hi> Or the <hi>Spices</hi> of the <hi>Spouſes Garden,</hi> not a <hi>Maſt</hi> hath beene ſet vp. Nay they can make ſhift, to ſhed <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Bloud, ſo farre off amongſt themſelues, and not a Drop for the Cauſe of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> But let me recall my ſelfe; I muſt acknowledge, that within the ſpace of fifty yeares (whereof I ſpake,) there haue beene three Noble, and Memorable <hi>Actions,</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Infidels,</hi> wherein the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> hath beene the <hi>Inuader.</hi> For where it is, vpon the Defenſiue, I reckon it, a <hi>Warre</hi> of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and not of Piety. The Firſt was, that Famous, and Fortunate <hi>Warre</hi> by <hi>Sea,</hi> that ended in the Victory of <hi>Lepanto;</hi> Which hath put a Hooke, into the Noſthrills of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:433:54"/> the <hi>Ottomans,</hi> to this day: Which was the Worke (chiefly) of that excellent <hi>Pope, Pius Quintus;</hi> whom I wonder his Succeſſours haue not declared a <hi>Saint.</hi> The Second was, the Noble, though Vnfortunate, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition,</hi> of <hi>Sebaſtian King</hi> of <hi>Portugall,</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Africke,</hi> which was atchieued by him alone; So alone, as left ſomewhat for others to Excuſe. The laſt was, the Braue <hi>Incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> of <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> the <hi>Tranſiluanian Prince;</hi> The Thred of whoſe Proſperity was cut off, by the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> themſelues; Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Worthy, and Paternall Monitories, of <hi>Pope Clement</hi> the <hi>Eight.</hi> More than theſe, I doe not remember.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>POL.</speaker>
                     <p>No! what ſay you, to the <hi>Extirpation,</hi> of the <hi>Moores,</hi> of <hi>Valentia? At which ſudden Queſtion,</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius <hi>was a little at a ſtop, and</hi> Gamaliel <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented him, and ſaid.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GAMALIEL.</speaker>
                     <p>I thinke <hi>Martius</hi> did well in omitting that Action, for I, for my part, neuer approued it; And it ſeemes, <hi>God</hi> was not well pleaſed with that Deed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For you ſee the <hi>King,</hi> in whoſe time it paſſed, (whom you Catholikes count a Saint-like, and Immaculate
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:433:54"/> 
                        <hi>Prince,)</hi> was taken away, in the Flower of his Age: And the <hi>Author,</hi> and great <hi>Counſellour</hi> of that Rigour, (whoſe For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes ſeemed to be <hi>built vpon the rocke,</hi>) is ruined: And it is thought by ſome, that the Reckonings of that Buſineſſe, are not yet clear'd with <hi>Spaine;</hi> For that Numbers, of thoſe ſuppoſed <hi>Moores,</hi> being tried now by their Exile, continue conſtant in the <hi>Faith,</hi> and true <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in all points, ſaue in the Thirſt of <hi>Reuenge.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEBED.</speaker>
                     <p>Make not haſty Iudgement, <hi>(Gamaliel,)</hi> of that great action; Which was as <hi>Chriſts Fanne,</hi> in thoſe Countries; Except you could ſhew, ſome ſuch Couenant, from the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> as <hi>Ioſuah</hi> made with the <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beonites;</hi> That that <hi>Curſed Seed</hi> ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the Land. And you ſee, it was done by <hi>Edict,</hi> not tumultuouſly; The Sword was not put into the <hi>Peoples</hi> Hand.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EVPOL.</speaker>
                     <p>I thinke, <hi>Martius</hi> did omit it, not as making any Iudgement of it, either way; But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſorted not aptly, with Actions of <hi>Warre,</hi> being vpon Subiects, and without reſiſtance. But let vs, if you thinke good,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:433:55"/> giue <hi>Martius</hi> leaue, to proceed in his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; For me thought he ſpake, like a <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine</hi> in <hi>Armour.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MARTIVS.</speaker>
                     <p>It is true, <hi>(Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis,)</hi> that the Principall Obiect, which I haue before mine Eyes, in that whereof I ſpeake, is Piety, and Religion. But neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, if I ſhould ſpeake only as a Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Man, I ſhould perſwade the ſame thing. For there is no ſuch Enterpriſe, at this day, for ſecular Greatneſſe, and terrene Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as a <hi>Warre</hi> vpon <hi>Infidels.</hi> Neither doe I, in this, propound a Nouelty, or Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but that, which is proued by late Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, of the ſame kinde, though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps of leſſe difficulty. The <hi>Caſtilians,</hi> the age before that wherein we liue, opened the <hi>New World;</hi> And ſubdued, and planted <hi>Mexico, Peru, Chile,</hi> and other Parts of the <hi>Weſt Indies.</hi> We ſee what Flouds of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, haue flowed into <hi>Europe,</hi> by that Action; So that the Cenſe, or Rates of <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> are raiſed ſince ten times, yea twenty times told. Of this Treaſure, it is true, the <hi>Gold</hi> was Accumulate, and Store Treaſure, for the moſt part; But the <hi>Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer</hi>
                        <pb n="101" facs="tcp:433:55"/> is ſtill growing. Beſides, infinite is the Acceſſe, of Territory, and Empire, by the ſame Enterpriſe. For there was, neuer an <hi>Hand</hi> drawen, that did double the <hi>Reſt,</hi> of the <hi>Habitable World,</hi> before this; For ſo a Man may truly terme it, if he ſhall put to account, as well that that is, as that which may be hereafter, by the further Occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Colonizing, of thoſe Countries. And yet it cannot be affirmed, (if one ſpeake ingenuouſly,) that it was the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation,</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> that was the Adamant of that Diſcouery, Entry, and Plantation; But Gold, and Siluer, and Temporall Profit, and Glory: So that, what was firſt in <hi>Gods</hi> Prouidence, was but ſecond in Mans Appetite, and Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The like may be ſaid, of the famous Nauigations, and Conqueſts, of <hi>Emanuel, King</hi> of <hi>Portugall,</hi> whoſe Armes beganne to circle <hi>Africke,</hi> and <hi>Aſia;</hi> and to acquire, not onely the Trade of Spices, and Stones, and Muske, and Drugges, but Footing, and places, in thoſe extreme Parts of the <hi>Eaſt.</hi> For neither in this, was <hi>Religion</hi> the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:433:56"/> Principall, but Amplification, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement, of Riches, and Dominion. And the Effect, of theſe two Enterpriſes, is now ſuch, that both the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and the <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> being met in the <hi>Crowne</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> it is come to paſſe, that as one ſaith in a braue kinde of Expreſſion; <hi>The Sunne neuer ſets in the Spaniſh Dominions, but euer ſhines, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one part, or other of them:</hi> Which, to ſay truly, is a beame of Glory, though I cannot ſay, it is ſo Solide a Body of Glory, wherein the <hi>Crowne</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> ſurpaſſeth all the former <hi>Monarchies.</hi> So as to conclude, we may ſee, that in theſe Actions vpon <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> or <hi>Infidels,</hi> onely or chiefly, both the Spirituall, and Temporall, Honour, and Good, haue beene, in one purſuit, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, conioyned.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>POL.</speaker>
                     <p>Me thinks, with your fauour, you ſhould remember, <hi>(Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,)</hi> that Wilde, and Sauage People, are like Beaſts, and Birds, which are <hi>Ferae Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae,</hi> the Property of which paſſeth with the Poſſeſſion, and goeth to the Occupant; But of Ciuill People, it is not ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MAR.</speaker>
                     <p>I know no ſuch difference, amongſt Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:433:56"/> ſoules; But that whatſoeuer is in order, to the greateſt, and moſt generall Good of people, may iuſtifie the Action, be the people more, or leſſe, Ciuill. But, <hi>(Eupolis,)</hi> I ſhall not eaſily grant, that the People of <hi>Peru,</hi> or <hi>Mexico,</hi> were ſuch brute Sauages, as you intend; Or that there ſhould be, any ſuch Difference betweene them, and many of the Infidels, which are now in other parts. In <hi>Peru,</hi> though they were vnapparrelled People, according to the Clime; And had ſome Cuſtomes very Barbarous; Yet the <hi>Gouernment</hi> of the <hi>Incae's,</hi> had many Parts of Humanity, and Ciuility. They had reduced the <hi>Nations,</hi> from the <hi>Adoration</hi> of a Multitude of <hi>Idols,</hi> and <hi>Fancies,</hi> to the <hi>Adoration</hi> of the <hi>Sunne.</hi> And, as I remember, the <hi>Booke</hi> of <hi>Wiſdome</hi> noteth Degrees of <hi>Idolatry;</hi> Making that of <hi>Worſhipping</hi> Petty, and Vile <hi>Idols,</hi> more groſſe, than ſimply the <hi>Worſhipping</hi> of the <hi>Creature.</hi> And ſome of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> as I take it, doe the like, in the Metaphore, of more vgly, and Beſtiall <hi>Fornication.</hi> The <hi>Peruuians</hi> alſo, (vnder the <hi>Incaes,</hi>) had
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:433:57"/> magnificent Temples of their Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; They had Strict and Regular Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; They bare great Faith, and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to their <hi>Kings;</hi> They proceeded in a kinde of Marſhall Iuſtice with their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, offering them their Law, as better for their owne Good, before they drew their Sword. And much like, was the State of <hi>Mexico,</hi> being an <hi>Electiue Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie.</hi> As for thoſe People of the Eaſt, <hi>(Goa, Calecute, Malaca,)</hi> they were a Fine, and Dainty People; Frugall, and yet Elegant, though not Militar. So that if Things be rightly weighed, the <hi>Empire</hi> of the <hi>Turks,</hi> may be truly affirmed, to be more Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, than any of theſe. A cruel Tyranny, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in the Bloud of their Emperours, vpon euery Succeſſion: A Heap of Vaſſals, and Slaues: No Nobles, No Gentlemen: No Free-men, No Inheritance of Land, No Stirp or Ancient Families: A People that is without <hi>Naturall Affection,</hi> and, as the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Regardeth not the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of Women:</hi> And without Piety, or Care towards their Children: A <hi>Nation</hi>
                        <pb n="105" facs="tcp:433:57"/> without Morality, without Letters, Arts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or Sciences; That can ſcarce meaſure an Acre of Land, or an Houre of the Day: Baſe and Sluttiſh in Buildings, Diets, and the like: And in a word, A very Reproach of Humane Societie: And yet this <hi>Nation,</hi> hath made the <hi>Garden</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> a <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe;</hi> For that, as it is truly ſaid, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Turks; Where Ottomans Horſe ſets his foot, people will come vp very thin.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>POLLIO.</speaker>
                     <p>Yet in the midſt of your Inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue, <hi>(Martius,)</hi> doe the <hi>Turks</hi> this right, as to remember, that they are no <hi>Idolaters:</hi> For if, as you ſay, there be a Difference, betweene <hi>Worſhipping</hi> a Baſe <hi>Idoll,</hi> and the <hi>Sunne;</hi> There is a much greater Difference, betweene worſhipping a <hi>Creature,</hi> and the <hi>Creator.</hi> For the <hi>Turks</hi> doe acknowledge <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Father, Creator</hi> of <hi>Heauen,</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> being the firſt Perſon in the <hi>Trinity,</hi> though they deny the reſt. <hi>At which Speech, when</hi> Martius <hi>made ſome pauſe,</hi> Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedaeus <hi>replied with a Countenance of great Reprehenſion, and Seueritie.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEBED.</speaker>
                     <p>Wee muſt take heed, <hi>(Pollio,)</hi> that wee fall not
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:433:58"/> at vnawares, into the Hereſie of <hi>Manuel Comnenus, Emperour</hi> of <hi>Grecia;</hi> Who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, that <hi>Mahomets God,</hi> was the true <hi>God;</hi> Which Opinion was not only reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and condemned by the <hi>Synode,</hi> but imputed to the <hi>Emperour,</hi> as extreme Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; Being reproached to him alſo, by the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> in thoſe bitter, and ſtrange Words, as are not to be named.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MARTIVS.</speaker>
                     <p>I confeſſe, that it is my Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that a <hi>Warre</hi> vpon the <hi>Turke,</hi> is more worthy, than vpon any other Gentiles, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels, or Sauages, that either haue beene, or now are, both in point of <hi>Religion,</hi> and in point of <hi>Honour;</hi> Though Facilitie, and Hope of Succeſſe, mought (perhaps) inuite ſome other Choyce. But before I proceed, both my Selfe would be glad to take ſome Breath; And I ſhall frankly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, that ſome of your Lordſhips would take your turne to ſpeake, that can doe it better. But chiefly, for that I ſee here ſome, that are excellent Interpreters of the <hi>Diuine Law,</hi> though in ſeuerall wayes; And that I haue reaſon to diſtruſt mine own Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:433:58"/> both as weake in it ſelfe, and as that, which may be ouerborne, by my Zeale, and Affection to this Cauſe. I thinke it were an Errour to ſpeake further, till I may ſee ſome ſound Foundation laid, of the <hi>Lawfulneſſe</hi> of the <hi>Action,</hi> by them that are better verſed in that Argument.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>POLIS.</speaker>
                     <p>I am glad, <hi>(Martius,)</hi> to ſee in a Perſon of your Profeſſion, ſo great Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, in that you are not tranſported in an Action, that warmes the Bloud, and is appearing Holy, to blaunch, or take for admitted, the Point of <hi>Lawfulneſſe.</hi> And becauſe mee thinkes this Conference pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpers, if your Lordſhips will giue me leaue, I will make ſome motion, touching the Diſtribution of it into Parts. <hi>Vnto which, when they all aſſented,</hi> Eupolis <hi>ſaid.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>POLIS.</speaker>
                     <p>I thinke, it would not ſort amiſſe, it <hi>Zebedaeus</hi> would be pleaſed, to handle the Queſtion; Whether a <hi>Warre,</hi> for the <hi>Propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> without other cauſe of Hoſtilitie, be lawfull, or no, and in what caſes? I confeſſe alſo, I would be glad to goe a little further; And to heare it
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:433:59"/> ſpoken to, concerning the <hi>Lawfulneſſe,</hi> not only permiſſiuely, but whether it be not Obligatory, to <hi>Chriſtian Princes,</hi> and <hi>States,</hi> to deſigne it: Which Part, if it pleaſe <hi>Gamaliel</hi> to vndertake, the point of the <hi>Lawfulneſſe,</hi> taken ſimply, will be Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat. Yet there reſteth the <hi>Comparatiue:</hi> That is, it being granted, that it is either <hi>Lawfull,</hi> or <hi>Binding,</hi> yet whether other Things be not to be preferr'd before it; As <hi>Extirpation</hi> of <hi>Hereſies; Reconcilements</hi> of <hi>Sohiſmes; Purſuit</hi> of <hi>Lawfull Temporall Rights,</hi> and <hi>Quarrels,</hi> And the Like: And how farre this <hi>Enterpriſe,</hi> ought either to wait vpon theſe other Matters; Or to be mingled with them; Or to paſſe by them, and giue Law to them, as inferiour vnto it ſelfe? And becauſe this is a great Part, and <hi>Euſebius</hi> hath yet ſaid nothing, wee will, by way of Mulct, or Paine, if your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips thinke good, lay it vpon him. All this while, I doubt much, that <hi>Pollio,</hi> who hath a ſharpe Wit of Diſcouery, towards what is Solide and Reall, and what is Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and Aiery, will eſteeme all this but
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:433:59"/> 
                        <hi>Impoſsibilities,</hi> and Eagles in the Clouds: And therefore wee ſhall all intreat him, to cruſh this <hi>Argument,</hi> with his beſt Forces; That by the Light, we ſhall take from him, wee may either caſt it away, if it be found but a Bladder; Or diſcharge it, of ſo much as is vaine, and not ſperable. And becauſe, I confeſſe, I my ſelfe am not of that Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, although it be an hard Encounter to deale with <hi>Pollio,</hi> yet I ſhall doe my beſt, to proue the <hi>Enterpriſe Poſsible;</hi> And to ſhew, how all <hi>Impediments,</hi> may be either remoued, or ouercomen. And then it will be fit for <hi>Martius,</hi> (if wee doe not deſert it before,) to reſume his further Diſcourſe, as well for the <hi>Perſwaſiue,</hi> as for the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult,</hi> touching the <hi>Meanes, Preparations,</hi> and all that may conduce vnto the <hi>Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe.</hi> But this is but my Wiſh, your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips will put it into better order. <hi>They all not only allowed the</hi> Diſtribution, <hi>but accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the</hi> Parts: <hi>But becauſe the Day was ſpent, they agreed, to deferre it, till the next Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Only</hi> Pollio <hi>ſaid.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>POLLIO.</speaker>
                     <p>You take mee right, <hi>(Eupolis;)</hi> For I am of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:433:60"/> opinion, that except you could bray <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome</hi> in a Mortar, and mould it into a New Paſte, there is no <hi>Poſsibilitie</hi> of an <hi>Holy Warre.</hi> And I was euer of opinion, that the <hi>Philoſophers Stone,</hi> and an <hi>Holy Warre,</hi> were but the <hi>Rendez-vous</hi> of Crackt Braines, that wore their Feather in their Head, in ſtead of their Hat. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, beleeue mee of Courteſie, that if you <hi>Fiue</hi> ſhall be of another minde, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially after you haue heard, what I can ſay, I ſhall be ready to certifie with <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> that <hi>Athens</hi> is mad, and <hi>Democritus</hi> is only ſober. And leſt you ſhould take mee for altogether Aduerſe, I will frankly contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the Buſineſſe, now at firſt. Yee, no doubt, will amongſt you deuiſe and diſcourſe many ſolemne Matters: But doe as I ſhall tell you. This <hi>Pope</hi> is Decrepit, and the Bell goeth for him. Take order, that when he is Dead, there be choſen a <hi>Pope</hi> of freſh yeeres, betweene fifty and threeſcore; And ſee that he take the Name of <hi>Vrban,</hi> becauſe a <hi>Pope</hi> of that Name did firſt inſtitute the <hi>Cruzada;</hi> And, (as with
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:433:60"/> an holy Trumpet,) did ſtirre vp the <hi>Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age,</hi> for the <hi>Holy Land.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EVPOLIS.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſay well; But be, I pray you, a little more ſerious, in this Conference.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The next day, the ſame</hi> Perſons <hi>met, as they had appointed; And after they were ſet, and that there had paſſed ſome ſporting ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chees from</hi> Pollio, <hi>how the</hi> Warre <hi>was alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die begun; For that, (he ſaid) he had dream't of nothing but</hi> Ianizaries, <hi>and</hi> Tartars, <hi>and</hi> Sultans <hi>all the night long,</hi> Martius <hi>ſaid.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MARTIVS.</speaker>
                     <p>The <hi>Diſtribution</hi> of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, which was made by <hi>Eupolis</hi> yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, and was by vs approued, ſeemeth to me perfect, ſaue in one Point; and that is, not in the <hi>Number,</hi> but in the <hi>Placing</hi> of the <hi>Parts.</hi> For it is ſo diſpoſed, that <hi>Pollio</hi> and <hi>Eupolis,</hi> ſhall debate the <hi>Poſsibility,</hi> or <hi>Impoſsibility</hi> of the <hi>Action,</hi> before I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, the <hi>Particulars</hi> of the <hi>Meanes,</hi> and <hi>Manner,</hi> by which it is to be atchieued. Now I haue often obſerued in <hi>Deliberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> that the Entring neare hand, into the Manner of Performance, and Execution of that, which is vnder Deliberation, hath
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:433:61"/> quite ouerturn'd the Opinion formerly conceiu'd, of the <hi>Poſsibilitie,</hi> or <hi>Impoſsibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</hi> So that Things, that at the Firſt ſhew, ſeemed <hi>Poſsible,</hi> by Ripping vp the Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of them, haue beene conuicted of <hi>Impoſsibility;</hi> and Things, that, on the other ſide, haue ſhewed <hi>Impoſsible,</hi> by the Declaration of the Meanes, to effect them, as by a Backe Light, haue appeared <hi>Poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> the way thorow them being diſcerned. This I ſpeake, not to alter the <hi>Order,</hi> but onely to deſire <hi>Pollio,</hi> and <hi>Eupolis,</hi> not to ſpeake peremptorily, or concluſiuely, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Point of <hi>Poſsibility,</hi> till they haue heard me deduce the <hi>Meanes,</hi> of the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And that done, to reſerue themſelues it liberty, for a Reply, after they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, as it were, a Modell of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe. This graue, and ſolid Aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Caution of</hi> Martius, <hi>was much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by them all; Whereupon</hi> Eupolis <hi>ſaid.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EVPOLIS.</speaker>
                     <p>Since <hi>Martius</hi> hath begunne to refine that, which was yeſter-night reſolued; I may the better haue leaue, (eſpecially in the mending of a Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:433:61"/> which was mine owne,) to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber an Omiſſion, which is more than a Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placing. For I doubt, we ought to haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or inſerted into the point of <hi>Lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> the Queſtion; How farre an <hi>Holy Warre</hi> is to be purſued, whether to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planting, and Exterminion of <hi>People?</hi> And againe, whether to enforce a new Beleefe, and to vindicate, or puniſh Infidelity; Or onely to ſubiect, the Countries and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; And ſo, by the Temporall Sword, to open a Doore, for the Spirituall Sword to enter, by Perſwaſion, Inſtruction, and ſuch Meanes, as are proper for Soules, and Conſciences? But it may be, neither is this neceſſary, to be made a Part by it ſelfe; For that <hi>Zebedaeus,</hi> in his wiſdome, will fall into it, as an incident, to the Point of <hi>Lawfulneſſe,</hi> which cannot bee handled, without Limitations, and Diſtinctions.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEBEDAEVS.</speaker>
                     <p>You encourage me, <hi>(Eupo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,)</hi> in that I perceiue, how in your Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (which I doe ſo much eſteeme,) I ought to take that Courſe, which of my ſelfe, I was purpoſed to doe. For as <hi>Martius</hi>
                        <pb n="114" facs="tcp:433:62"/> noted well, that it is but a looſe Thing, to ſpeake of <hi>Poſsibilities,</hi> without the Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>Deſignes;</hi> So is it, to ſpeake of <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe,</hi> without the Particular <hi>Caſes.</hi> I will therefore, firſt of all, diſtinguiſh the <hi>Caſes;</hi> Though you ſhall giue mee leaue in the handling of them, not to ſeuer them, with too much Preciſeneſſe; For both it would cauſe needleſſe Length; And we are not now in <hi>Arts,</hi> or <hi>Methods,</hi> but in a <hi>Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</hi> It is therefore, firſt to be put to Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion in generall, (as <hi>Eupolis</hi> propounded it,) whether it bee <hi>lawfull</hi> for Chriſtian Princes, or States, to make an <hi>Inuaſiue Warre,</hi> onely and ſimply, for the <hi>Propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the <hi>Faith,</hi> without other Cauſe of Hoſtility, or Circumſtance, that may prouoke, and induce the <hi>Warre?</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whether, it being made part of the Caſe, that the Countries were once <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and Members of the <hi>Church,</hi> and where the <hi>Golden Candleſticks</hi> did ſtand, though now they be vtterly alienated, and no <hi>Chriſtians</hi> left; it be not lawfull to make a <hi>Warre,</hi> to reſtore them to the <hi>Church,</hi> as
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:433:62"/> an ancient Patrimony of <hi>Chriſt?</hi> Thirdly, if it be made a further part of the Caſe, that there are yet remaining in the Countries, Multitudes of <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> whether it be not <hi>lawfull</hi> to make a <hi>Warre,</hi> to free them, and deliuer them, from the ſeruitude of the <hi>Infidels?</hi> Fourthly, whether it bee not <hi>Lawfull</hi> to make a <hi>Warre,</hi> for the Purging, and Recouery of Conſecrate Places, being now polluted, and Prophaned; As the <hi>Holy City,</hi> and <hi>Sepulcher,</hi> and ſuch other places, of principall Adoration, and Deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Fifthly, whether it be not <hi>Lawfull,</hi> to make a <hi>Warre,</hi> for the Reuenge, or Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of Blaſphemies, and Reproaches, againſt the <hi>Deity,</hi> and our <hi>Bleſſed Sauiour;</hi> Or for the Effuſion of <hi>Chriſtian Bloud,</hi> and Cruelties againſt <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> though anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and long ſince paſt; Conſidering that <hi>Gods</hi> Viſits, are without limitation of Time; And many times, doe but expect the Fulneſſe of the Sinne? Sixtly, it is to be conſidered, (as <hi>Eupolis</hi> now laſt wel remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred,) whether a <hi>Holy Warre,</hi> (which, as in the Worthineſſe of the Quarrell, ſo in the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:433:63"/> Iuſtneſſe of the Proſecution, ought to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed all Temporall <hi>Warres,</hi>) may be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, either to the Expulſion of People, or the Enforcement of Conſciences, or the like Extremities; Or how to be modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and limited; Leſt whileſt we remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber we are <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> we forget that others are Men? But there is a <hi>Point,</hi> that prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all theſe Points recited; Nay, and in a manner diſchargeth them, in the Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of a <hi>Warre</hi> againſt the <hi>Turke:</hi> which <hi>Point,</hi> I thinke, would not haue come into my thought, but that <hi>Martius</hi> giuing vs yeſterday, a Repreſentation of the <hi>Empire</hi> of the <hi>Turks,</hi> with no ſmall vigour of words, (which you <hi>(Pollio)</hi> called an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uectiue, but was indeed a true Charge,) did put me in minde of it: And the more I thinke vpon it, the more I ſettle in Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; That a <hi>Warre,</hi> to ſuppreſſe that <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,</hi> though we ſet aſide the Cauſe of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> were a iuſt <hi>Warre. After</hi> Zebedaeus <hi>had ſaid this, he made a Pauſe, to ſee whether any of the reſt would ſay any thing: But when he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued nothing, but Silence, and Signes of At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:433:63"/> to that he would further ſay, hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded thus.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEBEDAEVS.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Lordſhips will not looke for a <hi>Treatiſe</hi> from me, but a Speech of <hi>Conſultation;</hi> And in that Breuity, and Manner, will I ſpeake. Firſt, I ſhall agree, that as the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of a <hi>Warre,</hi> ought to be Iuſt; So the <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of that <hi>Cauſe</hi> ought to be Euident; Not Obſcure, not Scrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous. For by the Conſent, of all Lawes, in Capitall Cauſes, the Euidence muſt be full and cleare: And if ſo, where one Mans life is in Queſtion, what ſay we to a <hi>Warre,</hi> which is euer the Sentence of Death vpon many? We muſt beware therefore, how we make a <hi>Moloch,</hi> or an <hi>Heathen Idoll,</hi> of our <hi>Bleſſed Sauiour,</hi> in ſacrificing the Bloud of Men to him, by an vniuſt <hi>Warre.</hi> The <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of euery <hi>Action,</hi> conſiſteth in the <hi>Merits</hi> of the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> the <hi>Warrant</hi> of the <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction,</hi> and the <hi>Forme</hi> of the <hi>Proſecution</hi> As for the <hi>Inward Intention,</hi> I leaue it, to the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Heauen.</hi> Of theſe Things ſeuerally, as they may haue Relation, to the preſent Subiect of a <hi>Warre</hi> againſt <hi>Infidels;</hi> And
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:433:64"/> namely, againſt the moſt Potent, and moſt Dangerous Enemy of the <hi>Faith,</hi> the <hi>Turke.</hi> I hold, and I doubt nor, but I ſhall make it plaine, (as farre as a Summe, or Breefe can make a Cauſe plaine,) that a <hi>Warre</hi> againſt the <hi>Turke,</hi> is <hi>Lawfull,</hi> both by the <hi>Lawes</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>Nations;</hi> And by the <hi>Law Diuine,</hi> which is the Perfection of the other two. As for the <hi>Lawes Poſitiue,</hi> and <hi>Ciuill</hi> of the <hi>Romans,</hi> or other whatſoeuer, they are too ſmall Engins, to moue the Weight of this Queſtion. And therefore, in my iudgement, many of the late <hi>Schoolemen,</hi> (though excellent Men,) take not the right way in diſputing this Queſtion; Except they had the gift of <hi>Nauius,</hi> that they could <hi>Cotem nouaculâ ſcindere; Hew Stones with Pen-kniues.</hi> Firſt, for the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature.</hi> The Philoſopher <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> is no ill Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter thereof. He hath ſet many Men on worke, with a witty ſpeech of <hi>Naturâ Dominus,</hi> and <hi>Naturâ Seruus;</hi> Affirming expreſly, and poſitiuely; <hi>That from the very Natiuity, ſome Things are borne to Rule, and ſome things to Obey.</hi> Which Oracle
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:433:64"/> hath beene taken in diuers ſenſes. Some haue taken it, for a Speech of Oſtentation, to entitle the <hi>Grecians,</hi> to an <hi>Empire</hi> ouer the <hi>Barbarians;</hi> Which indeed was better maintained by his Scholler <hi>Alexander.</hi> Some haue taken it, for a Speculatiue Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, that Reaſon and Nature would, that the Beſt ſhould gouerne; But, not in any wiſe to create a Right. But for my part, I take it, neither for a Bragge, nor for a wiſh; But for a Truth, as he limiteth it. For he ſaith, That if there can be found, ſuch an Inequality betweene Man and Man, as there is betweene Man and Beaſt, or betweene Soule and Body, it inueſteth a Right of Gouernment; Which ſeemeth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an Impoſſible Caſe, than an vntrue Sentence. But I hold both the <hi>Iudgement</hi> true, and the <hi>Caſe</hi> poſſible; And ſuch as hath had, and hath a Being, both in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Men, and Nations. But ere we goe further, let vs confine Ambiguities, and Miſtakings, that they trouble vs not. Firſt, to ſay, that the more Capable, or the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Deſeruer, hath ſuch Right to gouerne,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:433:65"/> as he may compulſorily, bring vnder the leſſe Worthy, is idle. Men will neuer agree vpon it, who is the more Worthy. For it is not only in order of Nature, for him to gouerne, that is the more Intelligent, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> would haue it; But there is no leſſe required for Gouernment, Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to protect; and, aboue all, Honeſty, and Probity of the Will, to abſtaine from Iniury. So Fitneſſe to gouerne, is a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed Buſineſſe. Some Men, ſome Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, excell in the one ability, ſome in the other. Therefore the Poſition, which I intend, is not in the <hi>Comparatiue,</hi> that the Wiſer, or the Stouter, or the Iuſter Nation ſhould gouerne; But in the <hi>Priuatiue,</hi> that where there is an Heape of People, (though we terme it a Kingdome, or State,) that is altogether vnable, or Indigne to gouerne; There it is a iuſt Cauſe of <hi>Warre,</hi> for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nation, that is Ciuill, or Polliced, to ſubdue them: And this, though it were to be done, by a <hi>Cyrus,</hi> or a <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that were no Chriſtian. The ſecond Miſtaking, to be baniſhed, is; That I vnderſtand not this of
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:433:65"/> a <hi>Perſonall Tyranny,</hi> as was the State of <hi>Rome,</hi> vnder a <hi>Caligula,</hi> or a <hi>Nero,</hi> or a <hi>Commodus;</hi> Shall the Nation ſuffer for that wherein they ſuffer? But when the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the State, and the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Cuſtomes, and <hi>Lawes</hi> of the ſame, (if <hi>Lawes</hi> they may be called,) are againſt the <hi>Lawes</hi> of Nature, and Nations, then I ſay, a <hi>Warre</hi> vpon them is lawfull. I ſhall diuide the Queſtion into three parts. Firſt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be, or may be, <hi>any Nation,</hi> or <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> againſt whom it is lawfull to make a <hi>Warre,</hi> without a <hi>Precedent Iniury,</hi> or <hi>Prouocation?</hi> Secondly, what are thoſe <hi>Breaches</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> which doe forfeit, and deueſt, all Right, and Title, in a Nation to gouerne? And thirdly, whether thoſe <hi>Breaches</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>Nations,</hi> be <hi>found</hi> in any <hi>Nation,</hi> at this day; And namely in the <hi>Empire</hi> of the <hi>Ottomans?</hi> For the firſt, I hold it cleare, that ſuch Nations, or States, or Societies of People, there may be, and are. There cannot be a better Ground laid, to declare this, than to looke into the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:433:66"/> Originall Donation of Gouernment. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue it well; Eſpecially the <hi>Inducement,</hi> or <hi>Preface.</hi> Saith <hi>God: Let vs make man after our owne Image, and let him haue dominion, ouer the Fiſhes of the Sea, and the Fowles of the Aire, and the Beaſts of the Land, &amp;c.</hi> Hereupon <hi>De Victoria,</hi> and with him ſome others, inferre excellently, and extract, a moſt true, and diuine Aphoriſme; <hi>Non fundatur Dominium niſi in Imagine Dei.</hi> Here we haue the <hi>Charter</hi> of Foundation: It is now the more eaſie to iudge of the <hi>Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> or <hi>Reſeiſure.</hi> Deface the <hi>Image,</hi> and you deueſt the <hi>Right.</hi> But what is this <hi>Image,</hi> and how is it defaced? The <hi>Poore Men</hi> of <hi>Lyons,</hi> and ſome Fanaticall Spirits, will tell you, that the <hi>Image</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> is <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity;</hi> And the <hi>Defacement, Sinne.</hi> But this ſubuerteth all Gouernment: Neither did <hi>Adams</hi> Sinne, or the Curſe vpon it, depriue him of his Rule, but left the Creatures, to a Rebellion, or Reluctation. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if you note it attentiuely, when this <hi>Charter</hi> was renewed vnto <hi>Noah,</hi> and his <hi>Sonnes,</hi> it is not by the words, <hi>You ſhall haue
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:433:66"/> Dominion;</hi> But, <hi>Your Feare ſhall be vpon all the Beaſts of the Land, and the Birds of the Aire, and all that moueth;</hi> Not re-granting the Soueraignty, which ſtood firme; But protecting it againſt the Reluctation. The ſound Interpreters therefore, expound this <hi>Image</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> of <hi>Naturall Reaſon;</hi> Which if it be totally, or moſtly defaced, the <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Gouernment</hi> doth ceaſe: And if you marke all the Interpreters well, ſtill they doubt of the <hi>Caſe,</hi> and not of the <hi>Law.</hi> But this is properly to be ſpoken to, in handling the Second <hi>Point,</hi> when we ſhall define of the <hi>Defacements.</hi> To goe on. The <hi>Prophet Hoſea,</hi> in the Perſon of <hi>God,</hi> ſaith of the <hi>Iewes; They haue reigned, but not by me; They haue ſet a Signory ouer themſelues, but I knew nothing of it.</hi> Which Place pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth plainly, that there are <hi>Gouernments,</hi> which <hi>God</hi> doth not auow. For though they be ordained by his Secret Prouidence, yet they are not knowledged by his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed Will: Neither can this be meant of euill Gouernours, or Tyrants: For they are often auowed, and ſtabliſhed, as law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:433:67"/> Potentates; But of ſome Peruerſneſſe, and Defection, in the very Nation it ſelfe; Which appeareth moſt manifeſtly, in that the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſpeaketh, of the <hi>Signory</hi> in <hi>Abſtracto,</hi> and not of the <hi>Perſon</hi> of the <hi>Lord.</hi> And although ſome <hi>Heretickes,</hi> of thoſe we ſpake of, haue abuſed this <hi>Text,</hi> yet the <hi>Sunne</hi> is not ſoiled in Paſſage. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, if any Man inferre, vpon the words of the <hi>Prophets</hi> following, (which declare this <hi>Reiection,</hi> and to vſe the words of the <hi>Text, Reſciſion</hi> of their <hi>Eſtate,</hi> to haue beene for their <hi>Idolatry,</hi>) that by this Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the <hi>Gouernments</hi> of all <hi>Idolatrous Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> ſhould be alſo diſſolued, (which is manifeſtly vntrue,) in my iudgement it followeth not. For the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of the <hi>Iewes</hi> then, and the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of the <hi>Heathen</hi> then and now, are Sinnes of a farre diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Nature, in regard of the ſpeciall Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant, and the cleare Manifeſtations, wherein <hi>God</hi> did contract, and exhibit himſelfe to that <hi>Nation.</hi> This <hi>Nullity</hi> of <hi>Policy,</hi> and <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Eſtate,</hi> in ſome <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> is yet more ſignificantly expreſſed, by
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:433:67"/> 
                        <hi>Moſes</hi> in his <hi>Canticle.</hi> In the Perſon of <hi>God</hi> to the <hi>Iewes: Yee haue incenſed mee with Gods, that are no Gods, and I will incenſe you with a People, that are no People.</hi> Such as were (no doubt) the <hi>People</hi> of <hi>Canaan,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Seiſin</hi> was giuen, of the <hi>Land</hi> of <hi>Promiſe,</hi> to the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> For from that time, their Right to the <hi>Land</hi> was diſſolued, though they remained in many Places vnconque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. By this we may ſee, that there are <hi>Nations</hi> in <hi>Name,</hi> that are no <hi>Nations</hi> in Right, but Multitudes onely, and Swarms of People. For like as there are <hi>Particular Perſons,</hi> vtlawed, and proſcribed, by ciuill Lawes, of ſeuerall Countries; So are there <hi>Nations,</hi> that are vtlawed, and proſcribed, by the Law of Nature, and Nations; Or by the immediate Commandement of God. And as there are <hi>Kings de Facto,</hi> and not <hi>de Iure,</hi> in reſpect of the Nullity of their Title; So are there <hi>Nations,</hi> that are Occupants <hi>de Facto,</hi> and not <hi>de Iure,</hi> of their Territories, in reſpect of the Nullity, of their Policy; or Gouernment. But let vs take in ſome <hi>Examples,</hi> into the Midſt of
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:433:68"/> our <hi>Proofes;</hi> For they will proue as much, as put after; And illuſtrate more. It was neuer doubted, but a <hi>Warre</hi> vpon <hi>Pyrates,</hi> may be lawfully made, by any Nation, though not infeſted, or violated by them. Is it becauſe, they haue not <hi>Certas Sedes,</hi> or <hi>Lares?</hi> In the <hi>Pyraticall War,</hi> which was atchieued by <hi>Pompey</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> and was his trueſt, and greateſt glory; the <hi>Pyrates</hi> had ſome Cities, ſundry Ports, and a great part of the Prouince of <hi>Cilicia;</hi> And the <hi>Pyrates</hi> now being, haue a Receptacle, and Manſion, in <hi>Algiers.</hi> Beaſts are not the leſſe Sauage; becauſe they haue Dens. Is it becauſe the Danger houers, as a Cloud, that a Man cannot tell, where it will fall? And ſo it is euery Mans caſe. The Reaſon is good; But it is not all, nor that which is moſt Alleadged. For the true receiued Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, that <hi>Pyrates</hi> are <hi>Communes Humani Generis Hoſtes;</hi> Whom all Nations are to proſecute, not ſo much in the Right of their owne Feares, as vpon the Band of Humane Society. For as there are, Formall and written Leagues, Reſpectiue to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:433:68"/> Enemies; So is there a Naturall, and Tacite Confederation, amongſt all Men, againſt the common Enemy of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Societie. So as there needs no Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, or Denunciation of the <hi>Warre;</hi> There needs no Requeſt from the <hi>Nation</hi> grieued; But all theſe Formalities, the Law of Nature ſupplies, in the Caſe of <hi>Pyrates.</hi> The ſame is the Caſe of <hi>Rouers</hi> by <hi>Land;</hi> Such as yet are ſome <hi>Cantons</hi> in <hi>Arabia;</hi> And ſome petty <hi>Kings</hi> of the <hi>Mountaines,</hi> adiacent to <hi>Streights,</hi> and <hi>Wayes.</hi> Neither is it lawfull, onely for the <hi>Neighbour Princes,</hi> to deſtroy ſuch <hi>Pyrates,</hi> or <hi>Rouers;</hi> But if there were any <hi>Nation,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo farre off, that would make it an <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe</hi> of Merit, and true Glory, (as the <hi>Romans,</hi> that made a <hi>Warre,</hi> for the Liberty of <hi>Grecia,</hi> from a diſtant, and remote Part,) no doubt they mought doe it. I make the ſame Iudgement, of that <hi>Kingdome</hi> of the <hi>Aſſaſins,</hi> now deſtroyed, which was ſituate vpon the Borders of <hi>Saraca;</hi> And was, for a time, a great Terrour, to all the <hi>Princes</hi> of the <hi>Leuant.</hi> There the Cuſtome was, that
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:433:69"/> vpon the Commandement of their <hi>King,</hi> and a Blinde Obedience to be giuen there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, any of them was to vndertake, in the nature of a Votary, the inſidious Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of any <hi>Prince,</hi> or <hi>Perſon,</hi> vpon whom the Commandement went. This Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, without all queſtion, made their whole <hi>Gouernment</hi> void, as an Engine built againſt <hi>Humane Society,</hi> worthy by all Men to be fired, and pulled downe. I ſay the like, of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> of <hi>Munſter;</hi> And this, although they had not beene <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels</hi> to the <hi>Empire:</hi> And put caſe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that they had done no Miſchiefe at all actually; yet if there ſhall be a Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Conſent of People, that ſhall hold all Things to be lawfull; Not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to any certaine Lawes, or Rules, but according to the ſecret, and variable Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Inſtincts of the Spirit; This is indeed no <hi>Nation,</hi> no <hi>People,</hi> no <hi>Signorie,</hi> that <hi>God</hi> doth know: Any Nation, that is Ciuill, and Polliced, may (if they will not be reduced,) cut them off, from the Face of the Earth. Now let me put a Feigned
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:433:69"/> Caſe, (And yet Antiquity makes it doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, whether it were Fiction, or Hiſtory,) of a <hi>Land</hi> of <hi>Amazons,</hi> where the whole <hi>Gouernment,</hi> Publike and Priuate, yea the <hi>Militia</hi> it Selfe, was in the hands of <hi>Women.</hi> I demand, is not ſuch a Prepoſterous <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment,</hi> (againſt the firſt Order of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for <hi>Women</hi> to rule ouer <hi>Men,</hi>) in it ſelfe void, and to be ſuppreſſed? I ſpeake not of the <hi>Reigne</hi> of <hi>Women;</hi> (For that is ſupplied by Counſell, and ſubordinate Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates Maſculine,) But where the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment</hi> of State, Iuſtice, Families, is all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged by <hi>Women.</hi> And yet this laſt <hi>Caſe,</hi> differeth from the other before: Becauſe in the reſt there is Terrour of Danger, but in this there is onely Errour of Nature. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould I make any great Difficulty, to affirme the ſame, of the <hi>Sultanry</hi> of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maluches;</hi> where <hi>Slaues,</hi> and none but <hi>Slaues,</hi> bought for Money, and of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne Deſcent, reigned ouer Families of <hi>Freemen.</hi> And much like were the Caſe, if you ſuppoſe a <hi>Nation,</hi> where the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome were, that after full Age, the <hi>Sonnes</hi>
                        <pb n="130" facs="tcp:433:70"/> ſhould Expulſe their <hi>Fathers,</hi> and <hi>Mothers,</hi> out of their Poſſeſſions, &amp; put them to their Penſions: For theſe Caſes, of <hi>Women</hi> to gouerne <hi>Men, Sonnes</hi> the <hi>Fathers, Slaues Free-Men,</hi> are much in the ſame degree; All being totall Violations and Peruerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, of the Lawes of Nature, and Nations. For the <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> I perceiue <hi>(Martius)</hi> you haue read <hi>Garcilazzo de Viega,</hi> who himſelfe was deſcended of the race of the <hi>Incaes,</hi> a <hi>Meſtizo,</hi> and is willing to make the beſt, of the Vertues and Manners of his <hi>Country:</hi> And yet, in troth, hee doth it ſoberly, and credibly enough. Yet you ſhall hardly edifie me, that thoſe <hi>Nations</hi> might not, by the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> haue beene ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued by any <hi>Nation,</hi> that had onely Policy, and Morall Vertue; Though the <hi>Propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the <hi>Faith,</hi> (whereof we ſhall ſpeake in the proper place,) were ſet by, and not made part of the <hi>Caſe.</hi> Surely, their <hi>Naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> (being with them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in moſt parts of that Country, without all Vaile or Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,) was a great Defacement: For in the Acknowledgement of <hi>Nakedneſſe,</hi>
                        <pb n="131" facs="tcp:433:70"/> was the firſt Senſe of Sinne: And the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie</hi> of the <hi>Adamites,</hi> was euer accounted an Affront of Nature. But vpon theſe I ſtand not: Nor yet vpon their <hi>Idiocy,</hi> in thinking that <hi>Horſes</hi> did eat their Bitts, and <hi>Letters</hi> ſpeake, and the like. Nor yet vpon their <hi>Sorceries,</hi> which are (almoſt) common to all <hi>Idolatrous Nations.</hi> But, I ſay, their <hi>Sacrificing,</hi> and, more eſpecially, their <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> is ſuch an Abhomination, as (me thinks) a Mans Face ſhould be a little confuſed, to deny, that this Cuſtome, ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the reſt, did not make it lawfull, for the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to inuade their Territory, forfeited by the Law of Nature, And either to reduce them, or diſplant them. But farre be it from me, yet neuertheleſſe to iuſtifie the <hi>Cruelties,</hi> which were at firſt vſed towards them; which had their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſoone after; There being not One, of the Principall, of the firſt <hi>Conquerors,</hi> but died a violent Death himſelfe, And was well followed by the Deaths of many more. Of <hi>Examples</hi> Enough: Except we ſhould adde the <hi>Labours</hi> of <hi>Hercules:</hi> An
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:433:71"/> 
                        <hi>Example,</hi> which though it bee flouriſhed with much Fabulous Matter, yet ſo much it hath, that it doth notably ſet forth, the Conſent of all Nations, and Ages, in the Approbation, of the Extirpating, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellating of <hi>Gyants, Monſters,</hi> and <hi>Forraine Tyrants,</hi> not onely as lawfull, but as Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, euen of <hi>Diuine</hi> Honour. And this, although the <hi>Deliuerer</hi> came, from the one End of the <hi>World,</hi> vnto the other. Let vs now ſet downe ſome <hi>Arguments,</hi> to proue the ſame; Regarding rather Weight, than Number, as in ſuch a <hi>Conference</hi> as this is fit. The firſt <hi>Argument</hi> ſhall be this. It is a great Errour, and a Narrowneſſe, or Straightneſſe of Minde, if any Man thinke, that Nations haue nothing to doe one with another, except there be, either an Vnion in Soueraignty, or a Coniunction in Pacts or Leagues. There are other <hi>Bands</hi> of <hi>Society,</hi> and implicite <hi>Confederations.</hi> That of <hi>Colonies,</hi> or <hi>Tranſmigrants,</hi> towards their <hi>Mother Nation. Gentes vnius labij</hi> is ſomewhat; For as the <hi>Confuſion</hi> of <hi>Tongues,</hi> was a Marke of Separation, ſo the <hi>Being</hi>
                        <pb n="133" facs="tcp:433:71"/> of <hi>one Language,</hi> is a Marke of Vnion. To haue the ſame <hi>Fundamentall Lawes,</hi> and <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> in chiefe, is yet more; As it was betweene the <hi>Grecians,</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>Barbarians.</hi> To be of one <hi>Sect,</hi> or <hi>Worſhip;</hi> If it be a <hi>Falſe Worſhip,</hi> I ſpeake not of it, for that is but <hi>Fratres in Malo.</hi> But aboue all theſe, there is the Supreme, and Indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluble <hi>Conſanguinity,</hi> and <hi>Society,</hi> between <hi>Men</hi> in generall: Of which the <hi>Heathen Poet</hi> (whom the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> calls to witneſſe,) ſaith; <hi>We are all his Generation.</hi> But much more, we <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> vnto whom it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed in particularity, that all <hi>Men</hi> came from one <hi>Lumpe</hi> of <hi>Earth;</hi> And that Two ſingular <hi>Perſons,</hi> were the <hi>Parents,</hi> from whom all the <hi>Generations</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> are deſcended. We (I ſay) ought to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that no <hi>Nations,</hi> are wholly Aliens, and Strangers, the one to the other: And not to be leſſe charitable, than the Perſon introduced by the <hi>Comicke Poet; Homoſum, Humani nihil à me alienum puto.</hi> Now if there be, ſuch a <hi>Tacite League,</hi> or <hi>Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,</hi> ſure it is not idle, It is againſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:433:72"/> or ſome Body: Who ſhould they be? Is it againſt <hi>Wilde Beaſts?</hi> Or the <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> of <hi>Fire,</hi> and <hi>Water?</hi> No, it is againſt ſuch <hi>Routs,</hi> and <hi>Sholes</hi> of <hi>People,</hi> as haue vtterly degenerate, from the <hi>Lawes</hi> of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> As haue, in their very Body, and Frame of Eſtate, a <hi>Monſtroſity;</hi> And may be truly accounted, (according to the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples</hi> we haue formerly recited,) <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Enemies,</hi> and <hi>Grieuances</hi> of <hi>Mankinde;</hi> Or <hi>Diſgraces,</hi> and <hi>Reproaches</hi> to <hi>Humane Nature.</hi> Such People, all Nations are inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſed, and ought to be reſenting, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe; Conſidering that the <hi>Particular States</hi> themſelues, being the <hi>Delinquents,</hi> can giue no redreſſe. And this I ſay, is not to be meaſured ſo much, by the <hi>Principles</hi> of <hi>Iuriſts,</hi> as by <hi>Lex Charitatis; Lex proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi,</hi> which includes the <hi>Samaritan,</hi> as well as the <hi>Leuite; Lex Filiorum Adae de Maſſâ vnâ:</hi> Vpon which <hi>Originall Lawes,</hi> this Opinon is grounded: Which to deny, (if a man may ſpeake freely,) were almoſt to be a <hi>Schiſmaticke</hi> in <hi>Nature.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The reſt was not perfected.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:433:72"/>
                  <p>AN OFFER TO OVR LATE Soueraigne King IAMES, OF A DIGEST TO BE MADE OF THE Lawes of ENGLAND.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device of John Haviland</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>LONDON, ¶ Printed by IOHN HAVILAND for <hi>Humphrey Robinſon.</hi> 1629.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:433:73"/>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:433:73"/>
                  <head>To the King; OF A DIGEST TO BE MADE of the Lawes of ENGLAND.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Moſt Excellent Soueraigne.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and Acts, of Soueraigne, or rather Heroicall Honour, the Firſt, or Second, is the Perſon, and
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:433:74"/> Merit, of a <hi>Law-giuer. Princes</hi> that gouerne well, are <hi>Fathers</hi> of the <hi>People.</hi> But if a <hi>Father</hi> breed his Sonne well, or allow him well, while he liueth, but leaue him nothing at his death; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by both He, and his Children, and his Childrens Children may be the better; Surely the Care and Piety of a <hi>Father,</hi> is not in him compleat. So <hi>Kings,</hi> if they make a Portion of an Age happy by their good Gouernment, yet if they doe not make <hi>Teſtaments,</hi> (as <hi>God Almighty</hi> doth,) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a Perpetuity of Good may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to their Country, they are but Mortall and Tranſitorie Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactors. <hi>Domitian,</hi> a few dayes before he died, dream't, that a
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:433:74"/> 
                     <hi>Golden Head did riſe vpon the nape of his Necke.</hi> Which was truly performed in the <hi>Golden Age,</hi> that followed his times, for fiue Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsions. But <hi>Kings,</hi> by giuing their Subiects good <hi>Lawes,</hi> may (if they will) in their owne time, ioyne and graft this Golden Head, vpon their owne Necks, after their Death. Nay they may make <hi>Nabuchadonozors Jmage of Monarchy, golden from Head to Foot.</hi> And if any of the Meaner ſort of <hi>Politiques,</hi> that are ſighted onely to ſee the worſt of things, thinke; That <hi>Lawes</hi> are but Cobwebs, and that good <hi>Princes</hi> will doe well without them, and bad will not ſtand much vpon them; The Diſcourſe is neither
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:433:75"/> good, nor wiſe. For certaine it is, that good <hi>Lawes,</hi> are ſome bridle to bad <hi>Princes;</hi> And as a very <hi>wall about Gouernment.</hi> And if Tyrants (ſometime) make a breach into them, yet they molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie euen Tyranny it ſelfe; As <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons Lawes</hi> did the <hi>Tyranny</hi> of <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtratus:</hi> And then (commonly) they get vp againe, vpon the firſt Aduantage of better times. Other meanes to perpetuate the Memory, and Merits of <hi>Soueraign Princes,</hi> are inferiour to this. <hi>Buildings</hi> of <hi>Temples, Tombes, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces, Theaters,</hi> and the like, are honourable things, and looke bigge vpon Poſterity. But <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> gaue the Name well to thoſe workes, when hee
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:433:75"/> vſed to call <hi>Traian,</hi> that was a great <hi>Builder, Parietaria, Wall-Flower;</hi> Becauſe his <hi>Name</hi> was vpon ſo many <hi>Walls.</hi> So if that be the Matter, that a <hi>King</hi> would turne <hi>Wall-flower,</hi> or <hi>Pellitory</hi> of the <hi>Wall,</hi> with coſt he may. <hi>Adri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an's</hi> veine was better; For his minde was to wraſtle a fall with Time; And being a great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſour through all the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> when euer he found any <hi>Decaies</hi> of Bridges, or Highwaies, or Cuts of Riuers and Sewers, or Walls, or Banks, or the like, he gaue ſubſtantiall order, for their Repaire with the better. Hee gaue alſo Multitudes of <hi>Charters,</hi> and <hi>Liberties,</hi> for the comfort of Corporations, and Companies
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:433:76"/> in decay. So that his Bounty did ſtriue with the <hi>Ruines</hi> of <hi>Time.</hi> But yet this, though it were an excellent Diſpoſition, went but (in effect) to the Caſes and Shels of a <hi>Common-wealth.</hi> It was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to Vertue or Vice. A bad Man might indifferently take the benefit and eaſe of his Waies and Bridges, as well as a good; And bad People might purchaſe good <hi>Charters.</hi> Surely, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Workes of Perpetuity in <hi>Princes,</hi> are thoſe, that <hi>waſh the Jn-ſide of the Cup.</hi> Such as are <hi>Foundations</hi> of <hi>Colledges,</hi> and <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures,</hi> for Learning and Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of youth; Likewiſe <hi>Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> and <hi>Jnſtitutions</hi> of <hi>Orders</hi> and <hi>Fraternities,</hi> for Nobleneſſe,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:433:76"/> Enterpriſe, and Obedience, and the like. But yet theſe alſo, are but like Plantations, of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards, and Gardens, in Plots and Spots of Ground, here and there; They doe not till ouer the whole <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and make it fruitfull, as doth the Eſtabliſhing of good <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>Ordinances;</hi> Which makes a whole <hi>Nation,</hi> to be as a well ordered <hi>Colledge,</hi> or <hi>Foundation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This kinde of Worke, in the memory of Times, is rare e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſhew it Excellent; And yet not ſo rare, as to make it ſuſpected, for Impoſsible, Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, or Vnſafe. <hi>Moſes,</hi> that gaue <hi>Lawes</hi> to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was the Scribe of <hi>God</hi>
                     <pb n="144" facs="tcp:433:77"/> himſelfe, is fitter to be named for honours ſake to other <hi>Lawgiuers,</hi> than to bee numbred or ranked amongſt them. <hi>Minos, Lycurgus,</hi> and <hi>Solon,</hi> are Examples for Themes of Grammar Schollers. For ancient Perſonages, and Characters, now adayes, vſe to wax Children againe; Though that <hi>Parable</hi> of <hi>Pindarus</hi> be true; <hi>The beſt thing is Water.</hi> For Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and Triuiall Things are (many times) the beſt; And ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſpiſed vpon Pride, becauſe they are vulgar, than vpon Cauſe, or Vſe. Certaine it is, that the <hi>Lawes</hi> of thoſe three <hi>Law-Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers,</hi> had great <hi>Prerogatiues.</hi> The firſt, of <hi>Fame;</hi> Becauſe they were the Patterne amongſt the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians.</hi>
                     <pb n="145" facs="tcp:433:77"/> The ſecond, of <hi>Laſting;</hi> For they continued longeſt without alteration. The third, of a <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Reuiuer;</hi> To bee often oppreſſed, and often reſtored.</p>
                  <p>Amongſt the ſeuen <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> foure were <hi>Law-Giuers.</hi> For it is moſt true, that a <hi>Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer</hi> of <hi>Italy</hi> ſaith: <hi>There was neuer State, ſo well ſwadled in the Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, as the Roman was, by the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of their firſt Kings:</hi> Which was a principall Cauſe of the wonderfull growth of that <hi>State,</hi> in after times.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Decemuirs Lawes,</hi> were <hi>Lawes</hi> vpon <hi>Lawes,</hi> not the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall; For they grafted <hi>Lawes</hi> of <hi>Grecia,</hi> vpon <hi>Roman</hi> Stocke, of <hi>Lawes,</hi> and <hi>Cuſtomes.</hi> But ſuch
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:433:78"/> was their ſucceſſe, as the <hi>Twelue Tables,</hi> which they compiled, were the maine Body of the <hi>Lawes,</hi> which framed and weil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the great Body of that <hi>Eſtate.</hi> Theſe laſted a long time, with ſome <hi>Supplementals,</hi> and the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torian Edicts in Albo;</hi> Which were in reſpect of <hi>Lawes,</hi> as Writing <hi>Tables</hi> in reſpect of Braſſe; The one to be put in and out, as the other is permanent. <hi>Lucius Cornelius Sylla</hi> reformed the <hi>Lawes</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> For that Man had three Singularities, which neuer <hi>Tyrant</hi> had, but he. That he was a <hi>Law-Giuer;</hi> That he tooke part with the Nobility; And, That he turned Priuate Man, not vpon Feare, but vpon Confidence.</p>
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:433:78"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Caeſar</hi> long after deſired to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate him only in the Firſt; For otherwiſe hee relied vpon new Men: And for reſigning his Power <hi>Seneca</hi> deſcribeth him right: <hi>Caeſar gladium citò condidit, nun quam poſuit. Caeſar ſoone ſhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed his ſword, but neuer put it off.</hi> And himſelfe tooke it vpon him, ſaying in ſcorne of <hi>Syllae's</hi> Reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. <hi>Sylla neſciuit literas, dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re non potuit. Sylla knew no letters, he could not dictate.</hi> But for the part of a <hi>Law-Giuer, Cicero</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him the Attribute. <hi>Caeſar, ſi ab eo quaereretur, quid egiſſet in Togâ; leges ſe reſpondiſſet, multas &amp; prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claras tuliſſe. Jf you had asked Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar, what he did in the Gowne, he would haue anſwered, that he made
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:433:79"/> many excellent Lawes.</hi> His Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew <hi>Auguſtus</hi> did tread the Same ſteps, but with deeper print, becauſe of his long Reigne in peace; Whereof one of the <hi>Poets</hi> of his time ſaith;
<q>
                        <l>Pace datâ terris, animum ad Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilia vertit:</l>
                        <l>Jura ſuum, legeſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> tulit iuſtiſsimus Author.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>From that time, there was ſuch a Race of Wit and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, betweene the <hi>Commentaries</hi> and <hi>Deciſions</hi> of the <hi>Lawyers,</hi> and the <hi>Edicts</hi> of the <hi>Emperours,</hi> as both <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>Lawyers</hi> were out of breath. VVhereupon <hi>Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> in the end recompiled both; And made a Body of <hi>Lawes,</hi> ſuch as might be weilded, which him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:433:79"/> calleth gloriouſly, and yet not aboue truth; <hi>The Edifice or Structure of a ſacred Temple of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice;</hi> Built indeed, out of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Ruines</hi> of Bookes, as Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials, and ſome <hi>Nouell Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of his owne.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>Athens</hi> they had <hi>Sexuiri,</hi> (as <hi>Aeſchines</hi> obſerueth,) which were ſtanding <hi>Commiſsioners;</hi> Who did watch to diſcerne, what lawes waxed vnproper for the Times, and what new <hi>Law</hi> did in any branch croſſe a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Law,</hi> and ſo <hi>Ex officio</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded their Repeale.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>King Edgar</hi> collected the <hi>Lawes</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and gaue them the ſtrength of a Faggot bound, which formerly were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed:
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:433:80"/> Which was more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to him, then his Sailing about this Iſland, with a potent Fleet. For that was, as the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſaith? <hi>Via nauis in mari; The way of a ſhip in the</hi> Sea; It vaniſhed; but this laſteth. <hi>Alphonſo</hi> the <hi>Wiſe,</hi> (the ninth of that Name,) <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> compiled the <hi>Digeſt</hi> of the <hi>Lawes</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> Intituled the <hi>Siete Partidas;</hi> An excellent Worke, which he finiſhed in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen years. And as <hi>Tacitus</hi> noteth well; That the <hi>Capitoll,</hi> though built in the beginnings of <hi>Rome,</hi> yet was fit for the great <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> that came after; So that <hi>Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> of <hi>Lawes</hi> ſufficeth the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the <hi>Empire</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> which ſince hath enſued.</p>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:433:80"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lewis</hi> the eleuenth had it in his minde, (though he perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it not,) to haue made one conſtant <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>France;</hi> Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted out of the <hi>Ciuill Roman Law,</hi> and the <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> of <hi>Prouinces</hi> which are Various, and the <hi>Kings Edicts</hi> which with the <hi>French</hi> are <hi>Statutes.</hi> Surely he mought haue done well, if, like as he brought the <hi>Crowne,</hi> (as he ſaid himſelfe,) from <hi>Page;</hi> So he had brought his <hi>People</hi> from <hi>Lacquay;</hi> Not to runne vp and downe for their <hi>Lawes,</hi> to the <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill Law,</hi> and the Ordinances, and the Cuſtomes, &amp; the Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Courts, &amp; diſcourſes of Philoſophers, as they vſe to doe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>King Henry</hi> the Eighth, in the
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:433:81"/> twenty ſeuenth yeare of his Reigne, was authorized by <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> to nominate 32. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners, part Eccleſiaſticall, and part Temporall; To purge the <hi>Canon Law,</hi> and to make it agreeable to the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Law</hi> of the <hi>Land.</hi> But it tooke not effect. For the Acts of that <hi>King</hi> were (commonly) rather Proffers, and Fames, than either well grounded, or well purſued. But I doubt, I erre in producing ſo many examples. For as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaid to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> ſo may I ſay to your Maieſtie; <hi>Nil vulgare te dignum videri poſsit.</hi> Though indeed this well vnderſtood is farre from <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulgar.</hi> For that the <hi>Lawes</hi> of the moſt <hi>Kingdomes</hi> and <hi>States,</hi> haue
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:433:81"/> beene like Buildings of many peeces, &amp; patched vp, from time to time, according to occaſions, without Frame, or Modell.</p>
                  <p>Now for the <hi>Lawes</hi> of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> (if I ſhall ſpeake my Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of them, without partiality, either to my Profeſsion, or Country,) for the Matter and Nature of them, I hold them Wiſe, luſt, and Moderate <hi>Lawes:</hi> They giue to <hi>God,</hi> they giue to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> they giue to the <hi>Subiect,</hi> what appertaineth. It is true, they are as mixt, as our <hi>Language,</hi> compounded of <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh, Roman, Saxon, Daniſh, Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Cuſtomes.</hi> And ſurely, as our <hi>Language</hi> is thereby ſo much the richer; So our <hi>Lawes</hi>
                     <pb n="154" facs="tcp:433:82"/> are likewiſe by that Mixture, the more compleat.</p>
                  <p>Neither doth this attribute leſſe to them, than thoſe that would haue them to haue ſtood out the ſame in all Mutations. For no Tree is ſo good firſt ſet, as by tranſplanting, and Grafting. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what happened to <hi>Calli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſthenes,</hi> that followed <hi>Alexanders</hi> Court, and was growne into ſome diſpleaſure with him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he could not well brooke the <hi>Perſian Adoration.</hi> At a Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, (which with the <hi>Grecians</hi> was a great part Talke,) he was deſired, (the <hi>King</hi> being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,) becauſe he was an Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Man, to ſpeake of ſome Theme; Which he did; And
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:433:82"/> choſe for his Theme the praiſe of the <hi>Macedonian Nation;</hi> Which though it were but a filling Thing, to praiſe Men to their Faces yet he performed it with ſuch aduantage of Truth, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoidance of Flattery, and with ſuch Life, as was much applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Hearers. The <hi>King</hi> was the leſſe pleaſed with it, not louing the Man, and by way of diſcountenance, ſaid; <hi>It was eaſie to be a good Oratour in a pleaſing Theme;</hi> But ſaith he to him; <hi>Turne your ſtile; And tell vs now of our faults, that we may haue the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and not you the praiſe onely:</hi> Which he preſently did, with ſuch Quickneſſe, that <hi>Alexander</hi> ſaid; <hi>That Malice made him Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:433:83"/> then, as the Theme had done before.</hi> I ſhall not fall into either of theſe Extremes, in this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, of the <hi>Lawes</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> I haue commended them before for the <hi>Matter,</hi> but ſurely they aske much Amendment for the <hi>Forme;</hi> Which to reduce and perfect, I hold to be one of the greateſt Dowries, that can be confer'd vpon this Kingdome. Which Worke, for the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, as it is worthy your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties</hi> Act, and Times; So it hath ſome circumſtance of Propriety agreeable to your <hi>Perſon. God</hi> hath bleſſed your <hi>Maieſty</hi> with Poſterity; And I am not of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that <hi>Kings</hi> that are barren, are fitteſt to ſupply Perpetuity of
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:433:83"/> Generations, by perpetuity of Noble Acts; But contrariwiſe, that they that leaue Poſterity, are the more intereſſed in the Care of Future Times; That as well their Progeny, as their People, may participate of their Merit.</p>
                  <p>Your <hi>Maieſty</hi> is a great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in Iuſtice, and Iudicature; And it were pity, the fruit of that your Vertue, ſhould not bee tranſmitted to the Ages to come. Your <hi>Maieſtie</hi> alſo reigneth in learned times, the more, (no doubt,) in regard of your owne Perfection in Learning, and your Patronage thereof. And it hath beene the Miſhap of <hi>Works</hi> of this nature, that the leſſe Learned Time, hath (ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times)
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:433:84"/> wrought vpon the more Learned; Which now will not be ſo. As for my ſelfe, the <hi>Law</hi> was my Profeſsion, to which I am a Debter: Some little Helps I haue of other Arts, which may giue Forme to Matter; And I haue now, (by <hi>Gods</hi> mercifull Chaſtiſement, and by his ſpeciall Prouidence,) time and leiſure, to put my Talent, or halfe-Talent, or what it is, to ſuch Exchanges, as may perhaps exceed the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of an Actiue Life. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as in the beginning of my Troubles, I made offer to your <hi>Maieſtie</hi> to take paines in the <hi>Story</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and in compi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a <hi>Method</hi> and <hi>Digeſt</hi> of your <hi>Lawes;</hi> So haue I performed the
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:433:84"/> firſt, (which reſted but vpon my ſelfe,) in ſome part; And I doe, in all humbleneſſe, renew the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer of this latter, (which will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire Helpe and Aſsiſtance,) to your <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> if it ſhall ſtand with your good pleaſure, to imploy my Seruice therein.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:433:85"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:433:85"/>
                  <p>THE HISTORY OF THE REIGNE OF KING Henry the Eighth.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device of John Haviland</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>LONDON, ¶ Printed by IOHN HAVILAND for <hi>Humphrey Robinſon.</hi> 1629.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:433:86"/>
                  <pb n="163" facs="tcp:433:86"/>
                  <head>THE HISTORY OF THE REIGNE OF King <hi>HENRIE</hi> The Eighth.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the Deceaſe, of that Wiſe, &amp; Fortunate <hi>King, King Henry</hi> the 7, who died in the Height of his Proſperity, there fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed (as vſeth to doe, when the Sun ſetteth ſo exceeding cleare,) one of the faireſt Mornings of a <hi>Kingdome,</hi> that hath beene knowne in this <hi>Land,</hi> or
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:433:87"/> any where elſe. A young <hi>King,</hi> about 18. yeares of Age, for Stature, Strength, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and Beauty, one of the goodlieſt Perſons of his time: And though he were giuen to Pleaſure, yet he was likewiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous of Glory; So that there was a paſſage open in his Minde, by Glory, for Vertue. Neither was he vn-adorned with Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, though therein he came ſhort of his <hi>Brother Arthur.</hi> He had neuer any the leaſt pique Difference, or Iealouſie, with the <hi>King</hi> his <hi>Father,</hi> which might giue any occaſion, of altering <hi>Court,</hi> or <hi>Counſell</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the change, but all things paſſed in a Still. He was the firſt Heire of the <hi>White,</hi> and the <hi>Red Roſe;</hi> So that there was no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented Party now left in the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> but all Mens Hearts turned towards him. And not onely their Hearts, but their Eyes alſo. For he was the onely Sonne Of the <hi>Kingdome.</hi> He had no <hi>Brother,</hi> which though it be a comfortable thing, for <hi>Kings</hi> to haue, yet it draweth the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects Eyes a little aſide. And yet being a married Man in thoſe young yeares, it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:433:87"/> hope of ſpeedy Iſſue, to ſucceed in the <hi>Crowne.</hi> Neither was there any <hi>Queene Mother,</hi> who might ſhare any way in the Gouernment, or claſh with his <hi>Counſellours</hi> for Authority, while the <hi>King</hi> intended his pleaſure. No ſuch thing, as any Great and Mighty <hi>Subiect,</hi> who might any way eclipſe, or ouerſhade the <hi>Imperiall Power.</hi> And for the people, and <hi>State</hi> in generall, they were in ſuch lowneſſe of obedience, as Subiects were like to yeeld, who had liued almoſt foure and twenty yeares, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo politique a <hi>King,</hi> as his <hi>Father;</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo one who came partly in by the ſword; And had ſo high a Courage in all points of Regalitie; And was euer victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in Rebellions, and Seditions of the <hi>People.</hi> The <hi>Crowne</hi> extremely rich, and full of Treaſure, and the <hi>Kingdome</hi> like to be ſo in ſhort time. For there was no War, no Dearth, no Stop of Trade, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, it was onely the <hi>Crowne,</hi> which had ſucked too hard, and now being full, and vpon the head of a young <hi>King,</hi> was like to Draw leſſe. Laſtly, he was Inheritour
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:433:88"/> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Fathers Reputation, which was great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the World<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He had ſtreight <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>nce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with the two Neighbour States <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Enemy in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to times, and an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Fri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d, <hi>Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Burgundy.</hi> He had Peace, and Amitie with <hi>France,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Aſſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> not only of Treatie and League, but of Neceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e and Inhabilitie in the <hi>French</hi> to doe him hurt, in reſpect that the <hi>French Kings</hi> Deſignes were wholly bent vpon <hi>Italy.</hi> So that it may be truly ſaid, there had ſcarcely beene ſeene, or knowne, in many Ages, ſuch a rare Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of Signes, and Promiſes, of a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, and flouriſhing Reigne to enſue, as were now met in this young <hi>King,</hi> called, after his <hi>Fathers</hi> name, HENRY the Eighth. &amp;c.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:433:88"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
